<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An admonition moving to moderation, holding forth certain brief heads of wholesom advice to the late, and yet immoderate party. / By John Gaule, minister of Great Staughton, in the county of Huntington.</title>
            <author>Gaule, John, 1604?-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85866</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1916_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868851</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868851</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170560</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85866)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170560)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 237:E1916[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An admonition moving to moderation, holding forth certain brief heads of wholesom advice to the late, and yet immoderate party. / By John Gaule, minister of Great Staughton, in the county of Huntington.</title>
                  <author>Gaule, John, 1604?-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 125, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Lloyd and Roger Vaughan, for Henry Brome, at the Gun in Ivy-lane.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>[5] p. at end = advertisements for Henry Brome.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Moderation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170560:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ADMONITION Moving to Moderation, Holding forth certain Brief Heads of wholeſom Advice to the late, and yet Immoderate Party.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PHIL. 4.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let your Moderation be known unto all men; the Lord is at hand.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. de Gen. ad lit. l. 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Eſt etiam menſura aliquid agendi: ne ſit irrevocabilis &amp; immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derata progreſſio; &amp; eſt numerus &amp; affectionum animi, &amp; virtutum; quo ab stultitia deformitate, ad ſapientiae formam decuſque colligitur: &amp; eſt pondus voluntatis, &amp; amoris, ubi apponet quanti, quamque in appetendo, fugiendo, praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendo, poſtponendoque pendatur.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By JOHN GAULE, Miniſter of Great <hi>Staughton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Huntington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Lloyd</hi> and <hi>Roger Vaughan,</hi> for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the Gun in Ivy-lane. 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170560:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170560:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS Moſt Excellent MAJESTY Charles the II. By the Grace of God, of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King; Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt dread Soveraign!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides that your try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls have taught you Moderation, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with magnanimity; your Majeſty learned both of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im,</hi> that not only lived in
<pb facs="tcp:170560:3"/> both, but (oh horrour!) dyed for them. So that now your Moderation (as well as your Magnanimity) is become not only your erudition, and your Religion, but even your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo. VVitneſs thoſe your Gracious Letters, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations; the perfect model of a mind that is truly mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated with all graces and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: and ſo the abler to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate others, VVhich made me the more affraid of this preſumption, of caſting in this my ſmall Dropp, into that immenſe Sea of yours: (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit
<pb facs="tcp:170560:3"/> it were towards the quenching of our inteſtine conflagrations) and of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo dimme a Candle, before ſo bright and glorious a Sun. But (Great Sir!) I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, I ſaw (on your bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Birth day) a Starre at noon-day, look out with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant luſtre, though before, and near the then ſhineing Sun. Our Nativity-ſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers (who were not a little guilty in promoting the men of our portentous ſhame and miſery, to be what they were, and do what they did; through
<pb facs="tcp:170560:4"/> their deluſions meeting with thoſe of their own) durſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver meddle with this famous natalitiall Star; not ſo much as once to peepe at it. They know well I (for my part) am no Aſtrologer to Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticate. Yet can I (with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety I hope) affirme from a more ſure word of propheſy, it was a Light that ſhined, though in a dark place, to their Art; but in a light place, to your, and our hopefull Expectation (and we did well to attend it) till the day of Your, and Your
<pb facs="tcp:170560:4"/> Kingdomes happyneſſe, ſhould dawne; and that great <hi>day-Starre,</hi> both by His Graces and Comforts ariſe in Your heart. This <hi>day-Starre</hi> did ſignifie to our hopes; That although the morne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Your life might be ſomewhat (alas too much) benighted with afflictions: yet the noon-day of your fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity (and the Lord God promote it to be a perfect day) ſhould ſhine cleare. That you are choſen as a Starre, to ſhine before the <hi>Sunne of Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170560:5"/> That He that had his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <hi>Starre</hi> at His birth, was pleaſed to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe you yours alſo; that was borne to be his Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent here on Earth. To the end the wiſe-men of our Kingdomes might be guided in the right way, to come and honour you. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that we the leſſer Starrs might not be over dampt, in our preſumeing to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the glorious Sun of your Majeſtie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon (moſt Excellent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratour, both of Church,
<pb facs="tcp:170560:5"/> and State!) I am bold to crave acceſſe in preſenting you with a ſlender ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that, whereof you are known the eminent Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioner. Bold again, to ſay; It is ſufficiently known to your ſelf; what the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderation of zeale, Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentedneſſe, Ambition, Covetouſneſse, Fraud, and Force, hath both machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and perpetrated, to the diſtraction (well nigh the destruction) both of Church and State. But bleſſed be the great God of Heaven
<pb facs="tcp:170560:6"/> and Earth! who hath made good unto us that old max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime: <hi>no immoderate thing is diuturnall.</hi> And this (we truſt) you will make, and find as good: <hi>Nothing is to be firmely founded, or eſtabliſhed in either of them, but upon Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration alone.</hi> Theres no doubt therefore, but your Sacred Majeſty will be piouſly, and prudently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, and ordering in it. All the fear is, leaſt we our ſelves might fayle in the paſſive, or obſerving part
<pb facs="tcp:170560:6"/> thereof. God grant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we may make it our maxime alſo. <hi>Nothing can be eaſy, ſweet, and ſafe to us (in our lives, Religion, Conſciences, Lawes, Liberties, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties) without it.</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, we can never agree in the exerciſe of our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, either to God, or Man. Without it, we ſhall be tedious to our ſelves, and troubleſome to one another. Without it, we ſhall but wrangle, or wanton away our hopefull peace and proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:170560:7"/> againe: though that hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous outrage, with the grievous oppreſſion, and more then <hi>Mooriſh</hi> Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, that enſued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, be not as yet ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently (nor ever can be) abhorred, and bewayled. For this cauſe I have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted (as I was able) to make known this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Moderation in the Truth, and Fruits of it: that men might ſo learne, and labour after their own happyneſſe. Having mine in this, to be made known
<pb facs="tcp:170560:7"/> (among others) to be one endeavoring (by Gods grace) ſtill, as heretofore, to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate my ſelf, as becometh</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties Loyal Subject JOHN GAULE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170560:8"/>
            <head>ERRATA</head>
            <p>PAge 3. line 4. for walking, read ſo walking. and l. 2. dele only and read aſcertaining. p. 4. l. 21. for diſputed r. diſpoſed. p. 6. l. 16, evercovet r. overcovet. p. 7. l. 3. occaſion r. ovations. and l. 14 not. ſound r. out ſounded. p. 11. l. 23. obſervation. r. obſecration. p. 14. l. 17. out minder one minde. and l. 18. ſome r. ſo in. p. 16. l. 12. our moderation. r. one Moderatour. p, 17. l. 1. wall r. well. p. 23. l. 15. changed r. charged, p. 25. l. 14. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 28. l. 7. our part r. one part. and l. 8. ſo on r. ſo on. p, 35. l. 19. impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened r. importuned. p. 38. l. 3. principle r. principal. p. 39. l. 12. ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous r. ſynonymous, p. 40. l 12. formal r. female. p. 43. price r. peice. p. 45. l. 1. after r. as for p. 46. l. 14. aggreſtions r. aggreſſions. and l. 16. perpeſtions, r. perpeſſions. p. 49. l. 8. decoited r. decocted. and l, 13. care. r. feare. p. 54. l. 1. by being r. being by. p. 58. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. our uniformity r, one uniformity. p. 61. l, 13. ſo r. for. and l. 20. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 62, l. 4. affects r. effects. and l. 13. commended r. commanded. p. 64. l. 16. fit r. ſet. p. 68. l. 16. brings r. being. p. 69. l. 20. out r. but. p. 70. l. 9. our moderation r. one moderation. p. 71, l, 17. invitation r. imitation. and l. 10. our ſubject r. one ſubject. p. 73. if r, I. p, 77. l. r. evidencings, p. 81. l. 9. fall r. fell. p. 85 l. 24. ſoundneſſe r. fondneſſe. p. 86. l. 3. imperfectly r. in perfectly. p. 89. l. 21. as r. at. p. 95. l. 14. prickt r. pretended. p. 97. l. 4. laſt r. beſt. p. 103. l. 13. good ſo r. ſo good. p. 108. l. 5. r. overbending.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170560:8"/>
            <head>AN ADMONITION Moving to MODERATION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Phil. 4.5.</hi>
                  </bibl> Let your Moderation be known unto all men, the Lord is at hand.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F all vertue be well defined by a mediocrity, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting wholly in a middle betwixt two extreams. What a vertue of vertues then is Moderation? whoſe proper work it is, to labor both in the ſtudy and practice of that golden meane. Let vertue in it ſelf be never ſo equal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt exceſſes and defects; yet is it but a barren and ſloathful ſpeculation, not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170560:9"/> fruitful or beneficial to us, till this elective habit of a practical proportion bring it within the compaſs of lively operation. All her Equity is but as an idle number, till Moderation comes to give her her quickning meaſure. It ſerves indeed to ſet her even upon the very ſummity of affection and action, without either addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or diminution; yet trenches upon neither extremity, ſo as to alter the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and quality of the thing, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leaſt that appertains to the vitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of exceſs or defect. And as it holds an equal oppoſition to extreams of all other vertues, ſo eſpecially to thoſe of its own; being an apt mediety or medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity, betwixt the rigid contention of a furious zeal or emulation, and the luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm diſpoſition, of a reachleſs indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency or neutrallity, deteſting alike, to be <hi>over-juſt,</hi> and <hi>over-wiſe,</hi> as to be <hi>over-wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and over-fooliſh, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.16, 17. It approves of neither pace, to <hi>drive on furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly</hi> with <hi>Jehu</hi> in matters of policy, nor that he <hi>go ſoftly</hi> with <hi>Ahab</hi> in matters of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170560:9"/> piety. In matters of controverſie or ſcruple, or ſcandal, it likes well of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but of <hi>walking with a right foot,</hi> Gal. 2.14. And for walking, as <hi>to turn neither to the right hand nor to the left</hi> Deut. 5.32. And that alſo of choice, like the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> among the <hi>Edomites,</hi> Numb. 20.17. Not of conſtraint, as <hi>Balaams Aſſe</hi> between the two walls, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.26. It loves to <hi>churne</hi> the <hi>milk</hi> ſo as to bring <hi>but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> but hates to <hi>wring the noſe</hi> ſo as to fetch <hi>blood,</hi> Prov. 30.33. But above all, it hates ſo much as to hear of removing the ancient <hi>bounds</hi> or <hi>land-markes</hi> (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Religion or Laws) <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.14. For it knows there is a <hi>curſe</hi> thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing, to which every moderate man muſt ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> Deut. 27.17. Nay, and to break but the <hi>hedge</hi> (of a particular prerogative, priviledge, propriety) aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain onely it ſelf a <hi>Serpent</hi> will bite for it at laſt, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6.8. It in no wiſe endures the <hi>wiſdom</hi> that deſcendeth not from above but is earthly, ſenſual, devilliſh, where is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>vying and ſtrife, and confuſion, or tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170560:10"/> and every evil work, but delight in that wiſdom which is from above, as firſt pure, then peaceable, <hi>gentle or Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,</hi> and eaſie to be intreated, full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and good fruits without partiality, or wrangling, and without hypocriſie, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. And thus is this Moderation, not onely a Queen among morall vertues: but a miſtreſs and governeſs even in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual graces and duties. And ſo indeed it is admoniſhed by the Apoſtle in this place.</p>
            <q>Let your Moderation be known to all men.</q>
            <p>There is ſome difficulty, to conceive what conſequence this exhortation of the Apoſtle can have upon that immediately foregoing, or upon what connexion it comes in here? ſay it had none: yet there may be a method, whether the matter be ſynthetically or analytically diſputed; Divine Lawes and Leſſons are Aphoriſmes, not Declamations. And as for this of Moderation, it skilleth not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170560:10"/> much to enquire how it offereth it ſelfe, for (whether it be in ſpeaking or doing) it never findeth its order, but maketh it; yet leaſt want of ſome coherence might make it ſeem impertinent, let us expoſtulate a little with our Apoſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. Would he ſo earneſtly have them to <hi>rejoyce,</hi> (a good act of ſpiritual exultation) and it ſet upon a right ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject <hi>in the Lord:</hi> (contemplating the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, Perfection, Love, Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Benefits,) and exempt from carnal and creature-joyes. And that ſo inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, as <hi>alwayes</hi> (in act or habit, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity as well as proſperity) and that with a Repetition; <hi>Again,</hi> (to be renewed upon every occaſion, and extended to the utmoſt degree.) And that too upon his own warrant, experience, inculcation, <hi>I ſay rejoyce;</hi> Now then would he ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly recal that his incitation? or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect ſuch their conſolation, by an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate caution to Moderation herein: Is there any ſuch feare, that Theological vertues, and their ſpiritual affections,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170560:11"/> ſhould ſo ſoon degenerate, and be vitiated by exceſſe? Certainly, there can be no nimiety in exulting in grace, and the love of God, and <hi>Christ.</hi> Nay, there is no mediocrity that may here be admitted. No indeed; there can now be no exupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in reſpect to the primary object. But there are alſo ſecondary objects, and acts about thoſe objects; with the manner alſo of thoſe acts; all which may very well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh men to moderation. Though there can be no fear of redundancy, or ſuperfluity of ſpiritual graces; yet ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall delectations are here ſubject to the ſuſpition of both extreams. For a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man may ever covet the ſenſible and evidential comforts of them (which are not here to be ingroſt) and likewiſe may be too faint in the defect of their ſenſible evidence. And therefore uſes he this motive, in this very point; <hi>the Lord is at hand:</hi> viz. to come, and ſupply you with ſuch everlaſting comforts, and rejoycings, us ſhall need no moderation, becauſe ſubject neither to addition, nor diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170560:11"/> But does he not rather give the cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our ſpiritual exultations, to put a check upon our carnal occaſions? prayſed be our all provident God! who hath exceeding graciouſly given us of this Land occaſion of rejoycing, even beyond our expectation at this day. But I am greatly affraid of our immoderation, nay inordinateneſſe. That out Feaſting, and drinking of Healths, our Muſick, and Pageantry, our May poles, and Garlands, and Morrice-dancers, and ringing of Bells, our Drummes, and Trumpets, vollyes of Short, and ſhoutings; have not ſounded the ſoundneſſe of our hearts, both in the Ears of God, and men. I pray God give us grace to be moderate in our meates, drinks, apparel, paſtimes, or recreations, and revellings, in our vayne glories, boaſts, threats, preſumptions, expectations, leaſt the Lord ſee it, and be angry, and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to turn our mirth into mourning. But God grant us, to be merry in the Lord, after a more ſober, ſincere, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred way. And that inſtead of being
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170560:12"/> drunke with wine, wherein is exceſſe; we may be filled with the Spirit: ſpeaking to our ſelves in Pſalmes, and Hymnes, and Spiritual Songs, ſinging, and making me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodie in our hearts to the Lord. Giving thanks alwayes for all things unto God, and the Father, in the Name of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ:</hi> ſubmitting our ſelves one to another in the fear of God, that his delight may be in us, to rejoyce over us for our good; and go on (as he hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly begun) to turn all our ſorrowes into joyes.</p>
            <p>Further, to let you underſtand this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition was not without the Occaſion. Let us look a little higher to this purpoſe, and draw down the context from the two verſes before that aforeſaid. Thence you may obſerve with me: There was a kind of ſchiſme or diſſention, ariſing in the <hi>Philippian</hi> Church, (as what Church, even from that time, hath had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be without ſuch enormities? nay, what Church hath not been unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in them?) But this diviſion of theirs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170560:12"/> is nameleſs. For it ſeemed good to the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and the holy <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> to ſilence and conceal it, as touching what point, or what particular it was. And ſo indeed all ſchiſmatical diſſentions ought to be dealt withal. Its enough for the Church to complain that they are; though ſhe ſpeak not what they are, while errours and offences are but only known in their generals, Moderation may come in more eaſily to compound them, and that with leſſe noiſe, oppoſition and ſcandal, then when ſhe is put upon the ſcanning of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular. And therefore ſhe holds it both wiſer and ſafer, to ſilence them in groſs, then minutely to diſpute them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, how tender is ſhe to diſcover thoſe preciſe nakedneſſes, when ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives their Piety (for the main) obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in either Party, inviting to hide, nay, ſmother the ſingularities and perſonali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of each others infirmities? But oh the temerarious immoderacy of, or more then <hi>Cham</hi>-like immodeſty! How auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly have we defiled not only our own
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170560:13"/> neſts, but ript up our own mothers belly, and ſpit in our own fathers face? errours and perſons, crimes and names, how have we told them in <hi>Gath,</hi> and publiſht them in <hi>Askelon,</hi> to make the daughters of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> and uncircumciſed to rejoyce and triumph? what ſcandalous Miniſters have we made, till we made the Miniſtry it ſelfe a ſcandal? while we laboured, yea, and uſurped to the paradigmatizing of others, and they our betters. Wo, and alas! what have we done but ſtigmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed our ſelvs to the uttermoſt of infamy? by publiſhing our controverſies, of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery againſt Epiſcopacie, of Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry againſt Liturgie: of Independencie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſetled Miniſtry, and that grand quarrel of Oligarchy, or Anarchy againſt Monarchy: what hath all this immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate clamour prevailed? but to make us a reproach to our Adverſaries, a grief to moderate reformed Churches, and a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall to all good men, and a ludibrious hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the whole world.</p>
            <p>But to go on; This diſſention, it ſeems,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170560:13"/> began betwixt women. And ſuch hath alwayes been the immoderateneſs of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and affections in that Sex. And women (I wiſt) had a finger alſo in ours, when they ſacrificed, from their Plate, to their Thimbles and Bodkins; towards an Antiepiſcopal, if not Antimonarchical Warre, not unlike thoſe other, that break off their golden Eare-rings, to make up a molten Calfe. But I would to God, they had been women of no unworthier ranke and worſer report, then they ſpoken of in this place? And I would withall, that our men (a many of them) had not been ſo uxorious, and men womaniſh in this ſame caſe; Then certainly they had made a much earlier, and eaſier way to modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which indeed is the thing that the Apoſtle labors here, and he labors it by intreaty. For moderation works, and is wrought, not by abſolute commanding and impoſing, but by fair intreating, and perſwading. And his obſervation to this end is perſonall, mutuall, equall. <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech Euodias, and I beſeech Syntic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> O
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170560:14"/> rare way of <hi>Apostolike</hi> moderation! that hath reſpect to all Perſons, and yet without any reſpect of Perſons, modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is alwayes impartial, and nothing more partial, then immoderation. As we have ſeen, and heard, how ſome have bin wooed, and ſoothed even to flattery; and others (more conſcientious, and meriting) deterred, and checkt even to calumny and contumely. One party hath been entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to preach, and to print; and the other (abler for both, and honeſter in both) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden not the Preſſe only, but the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit alſo. One hath thanks given him for his paines, another hath paines ſet upon him, inſtead of thanks. To ſuch I will ſay with St. <hi>James. (Iam.</hi> 2.1, 4.) <hi>My Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, have not the faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Lord of glory, with reſpect of perſons.— Are ye not then partiall in your ſelves, and are become Iudges of evill thoughts?</hi> But if this work not with them, then I muſt ſay of them with St. <hi>Paul. The time will come when they will not endure ſound Doctrine, but after their own luſts ſhall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170560:14"/> they heap to themſelves Teachers, having itching Ears. And they ſhall turn away their Ears from the Truth, and ſhall be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Fables.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4. But I cannot paſs by that deteſtable immoderation of their horrible partiallity, in approving, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting only by tradition; making their own characters of men among themſelvs, and ſo taking the Teſtimony, and giving the verdict upon them accordingly. One they will have gifted, though ignorant; another ſhall not have grace, though learned. But the moſt horrid of all was, to hire or to call in Accuſers, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn; the accuſed unheard altogether, and unſeen. But our excellent Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor proceeds in his Moderating way; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching them both <hi>to be of the ſame mind.</hi> This verily is the way, and this the work of moderation. For there is nothing in all the World, that makes men to be more immoderate, then their being of many mind. Wheras Unanimity is the Mother, and Unity the Daughter of moderation. And they have a neer Kinſwoman, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170560:15"/> follows next after them; which they call Uniformity. He exhorts them to be of the ſame mind, not only between them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but even with the whole Church, of which they were Members. For mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is nothing betwixt particulars, except it be towards the general, or whole communion. We have known two diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters (of Perſons, and Factions) ſo to moderate, or ſuſpend, or diſſemble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as to conſent and combine to a more immoderate conſpiracy. Wherein they have proved like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate;</hi> made (as it were) unanimous Friends, or confederated, only for the uncontrolled (the paricidal, regicidal) crucifying of <hi>Chriſt</hi> their King. This being of our mind (in exact ſpeaking) is to <hi>reliſh, ſavour, reſent</hi> or <hi>be wiſe about</hi> the <hi>ſame thing.</hi> (For the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i y of moderation ought to be in minds, as in things: and ſome things, as minds.) And thus it implyes a moderate union, or united moderation in the ſenſe, will, and affections all at once. Now ſome have combined to follow their Senſes, or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuallities.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170560:15"/> Their wills, or wilfulneſſe; their affections, or affectations; without Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Some again, to follow their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or opinions, or rather deluſions; without any good will, diſpoſition, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection at all. And thus have they runne (headleſſe, and headlong) into the utmoſt of unlimitted immoderation in all their actions, and affairs. Now would ſuch had liſtened, how the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> limits it here; to be <hi>in the Lord:</hi> that is, according to Gods word, Spirit, Religion, good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and right Reaſon. Otherwiſe it will be (as it hath been) no unanimity, no moderation; but an immoderate aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, confederation, and conſpiracy, of Foxes tyed together, with firebrands in their Tales, or Rumps; raunging, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, to the conſumption of the good and fruitful Feild. Yea, and like to the <hi>Brethren in iniquity;</hi> of whom it was ſaid (and is to be ſaid) <hi>Inſtruments of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are in their Habitation. O my Soul, come not thou into their ſecret: unto their aſsembly, mine honor, be not thou united: for in their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170560:16"/> anger they ſlew a man, and in their ſelf-will they digged down a wall. Curſed be their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for it was fierce; and their wrath, for it was cruell. I will divide them in Jacob, and ſcatter them in Iſrael.</hi> Gen. 49.5, 6, 7,</p>
            <p>After he had thus concluded upon the matter, and defined the manner: See now, how he ſeeks, and ſues to the means, or inſtruments, for the apt compoſing of the fore-intimated differences. To a work of true moderation, the help of more then our moderation is required. And here alſo, to neglect the means (ſuch as may be moſt aptly inſtrumentall) is always to faile of the end. And good Lord! how have we forſaken our own mercy, in refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, nay and rejecting the means; and that through the moſt monſtrous abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of immoderation, that our Sun might be darkened, and totally eclipſed; only becauſe he labored to ſhine as a light, in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Our Glory put to ſhame, by the moſt ſhameleſs of all. Our Head ſpurned at by the very Heel, becauſe he propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170560:16"/> the wall governing of the whole body. Our father abdicated (by Baſtards ſurely and no Sons) becauſe he would have arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated betwixt the Brothers fallen at odds. Our Soveraign Phyſician maſſacred moſt barbarouſly; becauſe he endeavoured to have healed the Frenetick and Fanatick Patient. Our great and gracious Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratour mainly oppoſed, only becauſe he offered all he might to reconcile. Oh skilfull Pilot, unmercifully, and outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wrackt, becauſe he ſtood in the ſtorme, to ſave all, but himſelf. Oh! <hi>The breath of our noſtrills, the annoynted of the Lord, was taken in their Netts; of whom we ſaid, under his ſhaddow we ſhall live among the Heathen,</hi> Lament. 4.20. The Apoſtle invited both ſexes, (men and women) to moderate in this matter. But in that caſe, (woful caſe!) no ſex, age, degree, no Nation or Language, no Religion or Conſcience, no Praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Petition, would be admitted to moderate or mediate one whit. Oh, the abomination of immoderation; not infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170560:17"/> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it ſelf!</p>
            <p>To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>ting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>mendori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, <hi>Take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Goſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> Surely, he praiſed them not for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> preaching, nor once all owed a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, for to ſpeak in the Church? No, but for their other adminiſtrations, that might be advantageous thereunto. No, no, ſuch an immoderation and immodeſty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> never approved of, tolerated, or ſo much as connived at, until theſe our immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and inordinate times. But he denied them not (on neither part) their due praiſe, for other, their known graces, and vertues, Which was indeed the moſt ingenuous, and compendious way, to win them both fairly and briefly to a moderation, and union; As touching their leſſer conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſſentions. How farre otherwiſe was it with us, who were ſo immoderate, and disjoynted in Sects, and parts; as to deny, and diſclaime each others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and vertues. And all becauſe each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170560:17"/> would ackn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>edge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dly, but of his o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and gang, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> own, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f his o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> party and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of his own affec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>n, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that ran not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of riot. I had almoſt ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but of their own Errors; and enth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> But the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here ſpoke it, from a be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter diſcerning of Spirits; when be ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> even of theſe diſſenters, <hi>their names wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> written in the book of life,</hi> which undou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly be pronounced not upon their, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention, but as a motive, yea and perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their moderation. For nothing moves the very Elect more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> an accord here on Earth, then the thought, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of their recor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. But Lord! how were we reprobated, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by thoſe that had moſt need to examin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelves, and prove their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelues, whether they were not the repre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap> we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they ſhall know th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170560:18"/> reprobates. Nor will we ſay, they are, but hope their following moderation will make it known they are not. If they will convert with ſome of the exorciſts, let them bring their books together and burn them before all men. Even thoſe black books, in which both the Miniſters, and the Magiſtrates of <hi>England</hi> were deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phered, and as it were proſcribed, either to calumny, or confuſion. Elſe we may juſtly fear, their names are writ in that fearfull black book; who reſolve to live, and dye, in their diſſenſions, diviſions, ſeperations, factions, fanaticiſmes, ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, treaſons, rebellions: and (which is worſt) in the immoderations of them all.</p>
            <p>Well! Moderation now having hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſped, or happily done her work. Mark now! how ſhe invites to partake the Fruits, <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord,</hi> ſeeing ye are now of the ſame mind in the Lord, and that with all the extentions, and inculcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as before. I adde, upon the Authority, and temperament of moderation. Which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170560:18"/> he will have now proclaimed to all, though their diſſenſion was concealed. <hi>Let your moderation be known unto all men.</hi> How happy a thing is it, when mens diſſenſions are not known, but ſo, as folded up in their moderations? would God ours were ſo wrapt up! we need not care who knew it. But alas! all men know our diviſions; but what man knowes our moderation. That is revealed, which ſhould be conceald, and that is conceald, which ſhould be revealed, and ſo we go altogether by contraries. And ſhall their glory and rejoycing be alwayes, and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether our ſhame and miſery? Now mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy forbid it. Sirs! Ye are Brethren, let there be no longer ſtrife betwixt you. Behold how good and joyful a thing it is, for Brethren to dwell together in unity: (unity of Doctrine, unity of Diſcipline, unity of communion, unity of commerce, unity of Adminiſtration and Officiating; for it is eſpecially ſpoken of the Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Brethren.) If there be any Oyle of moderation, to cauſe you to account that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170560:19"/> conſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ting <hi>Oyle</hi> which was powred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>head</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ecious; ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e no more ſo f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, I pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y you, pull him not by the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> by which it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nne: nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of his G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> down to which it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> us revere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>der and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſo the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmon,</hi> (the grace, and comfort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of moderation and concord) may fall upon the Hill of <hi>Zion</hi> (the Church of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>) For there the Lord hath <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot in promiſe only, but effect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the bleſſing (here) and (hereafter) like for evermore.</p>
            <p>Now<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that ye may perceive, this Text reſpects, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only that which wear before, bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her which followes alſo. It ſo eaſily and neceſſarily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the ſubſequent voi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. That it is not ſafe for him to ſay <hi>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>full for nothing)</hi> nor for you to receive it as f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd unleſs you underſtand him, as indeed he me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s; <hi>viz.</hi> immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, and after an inordinate manner. Yea, the next clauſes ſtand (not out, but (as the ſcope of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi>) come in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170560:19"/> very p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this purpoſe. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (thou good things) or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pplication</hi> (againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) or <hi>Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> received benefits) your <hi>Requeſts</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g of occaſion) cannot be <hi>made known</hi> (that is approved) to God: unleſs in theſe externalls and temporalls eſpecially your moderation be known not only to God; but men alſo, which puts me in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> immoderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mens prayers for Warre, and blood; with thoſe of their Thankſgivings, for ſad Victories and outward ſucceſſe. How in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things, and wayes; they appealed, expoſtul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted, challenged, changed, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, owned, adjured, obliged, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, directed, pretended, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oaſted, tempted, and even mocked God. Hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other ground and aſſurance in all theſe, but the Spirits (Oh enthuſiaſtical!) moving, without the word. And his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret will permitting of ſucceſſes (Oh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>ticall!) without the warrant, and approbation of his will revealed. When that almoſt deicidall murder was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170560:20"/> committed; what ground, or Law had they for it? but (as they ſaid themſelves) their own ſeeking of God by prayer; and his immediate anſwer. (Oh fanatick, and nefarious Blaſphemy) and Amen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to?</p>
            <p>Let us now go a little lower. And as above we had the Occaſion, the Means or Inſtruments, and the fruitfull Iſſue: ſo below we ſhall find the Matter, the Example, and the End of Moderation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Matter; <hi>Whatſoever things are true.</hi> (Whether in doctrine, diſcipline, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or manners: For there is no thinking to find true moderation in a falſe matter. We found that too true, in the falſe moderating or purging of the Parliament; the new modelling of the Army; the new erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a high Court of Juſtice; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitatorſhip, Major Generalſhip, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Safety, and in the Protectorſhip it ſelf. To ſay nothing of the Exceſſive, or Defective Errours, and Feignings; of Presbytery, Independency, Anabaptiſme, and (the ſcumme of all) Quakeriſme.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170560:20"/> 
               <hi>Whatſoever things are honeſt, or venerable.</hi> Yea, the word ſignifies alſo <hi>grave,</hi> and <hi>comely:</hi> and poynts mainly at a <hi>decorum,</hi> in Perſons, Manners, Offices, Geſtures, Veſtures, and ſacred Places. About all which moderation is moſtly converſant, and to which it is moſt convenient. And we ſee ſufficiently, what an unhoneſt, and unhandſome <hi>indecorum</hi> immoderation hath wrought hitherto in all theſe. <hi>Whatſoever things are juſt.</hi> Here the Schoolmen more aptly place the thing of Moderation, then hence derive the name (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) making it an equitable and convenient part of Juſtice, to regulate and direct the rigour and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Lawes, according to their wholeſome intention rather then ſtrict words: for the common good, and the particular relief of certain perſons, in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain facts; the contingencies and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances well conſidered, contrary to the unjuſt immoderations of ſo many <hi>Draconick</hi> Lawes, Edicts, Impoſitions, and Exactions, of ſubſcribing, ſwearing,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170560:21"/> proteſting, cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing, confederating, aſſociating, eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ging, addreſſing, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring, <hi>Whenſoever things are p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> For Moderation is alſo apart of Temperance; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is in the modeſty of the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t in the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er man. <hi>Whatſoever things are lovely.</hi> And here alſo it is this fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dly Moderation of men and manners, than renders all matters i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church, State, City, Country, Pariſhes, and private f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ties) ſo amiable, and ſo mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able: labouring thus to recone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them, and ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them; Contrarily, how odious and inimical was our immoderation, that made us call and count thoſe of our own Religion, nay, thoſe of our own blood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The Common Enemy, <hi>Whatſoever things are of good Report.</hi> How famous Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is would be known, and it is partly from this, that all men know how infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous immoderation hath alwayes been: without Moderation, good things loſe of their name and fame; Indifferent things have none in themſelves at all but what
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170560:21"/> they borrow from it; and even bad things have their infamy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned by it. It is only Moderation that gains a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to men and things, and keeps it too, and promotes it alſo. However immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate men have affected a good report, even from things of a bad report, And have preſumed to raiſe a good name to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, only by taking away that of others. Yea, they have covered and conceited a fame from infamous actions. And 'tis not ſtrange to ſee or hear of it; for ſuch hath alwayes been the folly and madneſs of immoderate ambition. Yet (me thinks) this is ſtrange, that the infamy ſhould be inured upon nothing elſe but Moderation. Who bore all the brand at firſt, but moderate men from both ſides? And that under the Nickname (forſooth) of deteſtable Neutralliſts. But fierce friends, I beſeech you, If no body had ſtirred on either ſide, where bad all this ſtirre been? If no man had medled, had there not (think you) been more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence on the one ſide, and leſſe guilt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170560:22"/> on the other? without all doubt, the firſt brunt had been brought to nothing; if that the ſeconds (of Citty and Country) had not flockt in ſo faſt, to the making of the Fray. Even in forreign Warres, the cauſe can be juſt, and good, but upon our part: In Civill Wars, it is ſeldome ſo on either, (where all things are to be moderated not by Arms, but Laws.) More ſeldome when it is of the Inferior a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Superior, or of the private againſt the publick. In a word, know this; moderate men, though they have not bin the greateſt Sticklers, yet they have been none of the leaſt Sufferers. And likewiſe, whatſoever was wrong, the right hath prevailed at length; not by others Swords, but their prayers. And verily, <hi>if there be any vertue</hi> (intellectuall, morall, or the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologicall) it muſt be in moderation: which is both the Center, and Circle of all vertues. And therefore, <hi>if there be any praiſe</hi> (as the reward of a good conſcience, or a good work from God, or men) mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration will obtain (on all hands) at
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170560:22"/> laſt. Wherefore <hi>think on theſe things.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe things of moderations are not for light opinions, conjectures, ſuſpicions, fancies, humours, affectations: but for ſerious meditation, ſolid ratiocination, ſober reputation, certain reſolution, firme concluſion, and diligent endeavour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Example. See it, and hear it; for thus ſaith he that gives it. <hi>Theſe things which ye have both learned</hi> (as true Doctrine) and <hi>received</hi> (as good Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline) <hi>and heard</hi> (by my preaching) <hi>and ſeen in me</hi> (my exemplary practice) <hi>do</hi> (in a reall imitation) Or, which ye have <hi>learned</hi> (to informe your underſtandings) and <hi>received</hi> (to guide your affections) and <hi>heard</hi> (to ſatisfie your conſciences) and <hi>ſeen in me</hi> (to direct your converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) <hi>doe.</hi> And do theſe things indeed as well as think of them. For things of moderation (whether in Doctrine, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, Conſcience, or Manners) are not for contemplation only, and diſcourſe: but for practice alſo, and execution. We all can ſpeculate, and exhort to moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170560:23"/> in all theſe things: but who, and what is the Preſident and Example? we eaſily obſerve the paſſive party alwayes, and earneſtly pleading for it: but when (on when) ſhall we ſee the active peny endeavour to any performance of it? If we ſhould do no other, then what we have either (learned by obſervation) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived (by cuſtome) heard (by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint) or ſeen (by experience) in this particular: I am affraid we ſhould all be immoderate enough.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The End, <hi>The God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi> God is the God of peace within, and the God of order without. And as both, and in both, is with the unfeignedly moderate, by his promiſe, preſence, direction, and bleſſing. With whom then (I wonder) was that Devil of Warm, and diſorder? or with whom already are many of thoſe diabolicall Inſtruments that lived, and acted, and dyed immoderately; ſome ſo Diſtracted; ſome ſo Deſperate? But ſet them alone to ſtand or to fall to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170560:23"/> their own Maſter. Albeit, we may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſing, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e cannot abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ſay their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od was to be burned. How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, we are p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſwaded be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> things of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> moderate men; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> accompany ſalvation. For the God of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall not only be with them, but wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Peace of God</hi> (int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d in their conſciences, and external in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffairs) <hi>And ſuch a Peace as paſſeth underſtanding,</hi> (it is meant of cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d mindes, whether of Angels or Men) to apprehend compleatly, or intirely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e, eſpecially while mortality end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>. But we poor mortals (bleſſed be the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal God!) have now alſo a peace ſubject to our ſenſes, or happily c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me home to our very ſenſible experiments. And yet ſurpaſſing our underſtandin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, namely, when we go about to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> or conſider, by what meanes it hath pleaſed Almighty God, (who can work without meanes, and againſt meanes) to bring it thus about. We can impute it to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170560:24"/> nothing (under him,) but to the pious and prudent deſigns, conſultations, votes, and reſolutions of very moderate men; And that when all eyes were failing, all hands were feeble, and all hearts were faynt. To the end it might be known to be his own work alone. For which (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and again) yea, everlaſtingly let his holy Name have the praiſe, and that peace of his (we hope) ſhall now keep us in this of ours. <hi>Shall keep</hi> as with a <hi>watch,</hi> and <hi>guard.</hi> For which ſtill to the all Provident God be the bleſſing, the honour, and the praiſe! And (next to the Tutelary Angells) thanks to that <hi>Preſidiary Souldier,</hi> with that <hi>Preſidenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary Aſſembly.</hi> Whoſe gravely mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Counſells (as a ſafe cuſtody) we truſt, will <hi>wall</hi> us about, againſt the <hi>ſeiging</hi> of our open, and the <hi>undermine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of all our ſecret Enemies, As we pray the good God of Heaven, to keep both their, and our <hi>hearts, and minds</hi> (in ſound judgment, and ſober affections) againſt all the Temptations of <hi>Satan</hi> himſelf;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170560:24"/> and of all his Miniſters. Yea, though <hi>Satan</hi> ſhould transforme himſelf into an Angell of light (as he did of late) and though his Miniſters ſhould transforme themſelves into Miniſters of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as they are ready enough to do, that can change themſelves upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. Againſt all which, the Lord keep their, and our hearts, and minds, <hi>through Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> Both through the merits, promiſes, and mediation, and in the faith, profeſſion, yea, and even the moderation of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> our Lord.</p>
            <p>Thus hath this Text and Truth lookt round about to furniſh it ſelf from acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſories, and appendents. Now look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as a Continent fortified ſufficiently within it ſelf, and ſtanding altogether upon its own ſtrength. Or view it as an intire compact of a goodly Fabrick raiſed upon two mayne Pillars. Where had I but the Keys to let a man into every room and cloſet, he might ſee to ſatisfie a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous mind: and could I but open every Caſement, might diſcerne a proſpect
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170560:25"/> large and fayre enough to delight even a curious Eye. Firſt, take notice of the two Pillars.</p>
            <p>Which are
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>An Admonition.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>A Motive.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> The Admonition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let your Moderation be known unto all men.</hi> In which are notable; 1. The Perſon admoniſhing, <hi>Saint Paul.</hi> 2. The vertue, or thing admoniſhed, <hi>moderation.</hi> 3. The Subject, or Relation, <hi>your mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> 4. The Manifeſtation, or Evidence, <hi>Let it be known.</hi> 5. The object, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, <hi>unto all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The Perſon here admoniſhing. It is <hi>St. Paul</hi> the great <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and he a pure moderate man. 1. An Apoſtle. Know then; it is for Superiors (and ſuch as are emine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tly called in Church, or State) to be the Admoniſhers: and for Inferiors (in their private callings) to be the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers of moderation. Their part is to be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170560:25"/> the Agents: and ours to be the Patients in it. To give Laws, to our Lawgivers: regulate our Rulers; or moderate our Moderatours: if immoderate Polyprag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſts, and Allotricepiſcopiſts will u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpe it; yet is it not for us, that would be accounted moderate men, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take it. Be it for our Governour to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe it, and injoyne it. Be it for us to pray for it, and expect it. And let us be admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed withal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, beſides preſumptuous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, there have been, and may be even immoderate Petitions for moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Perhaps they proceeded from that old politick proverb: <hi>Aske an unequall, and an immoderate thing: that a moderate, and equall may be obtained.</hi> But they ſhould be ſo politick, as to be adviſed, by whom, and from whom, it is to be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portened. Otherwiſe, beggars that would be their own inſatiate carvers may well be ſent away without their Almes. And moderate men do count an immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate arrogator to do as much, as deny himſelf his own ſuit. 2. A moderate
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170560:26"/> man. For ſo indeed he was; according to that compleat character given of, and by himſelf. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19, 20, 21, 22, 23— <hi>I am made all things to all men</hi>—But the immoderate man ſayes quite contrary: <hi>I would have all men made all things to me.</hi> Thus you may diſtinguiſh them by their motto's, and their manners are accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. For the one condeſcends to others neceſſities, capacities, conveniences, advantages: the other muſt have all apply to his own opinion, humor, fancy, affectation. One makes himſelf a <hi>Servant,</hi> where he was <hi>free:</hi> the other makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Tyrant, where he was a Slave. One becomes a <hi>Jew</hi> to the <hi>Jews</hi> (complying with them) in all lawful obſervations: the other becomes a Jew even to Chriſtians; compelling them to undergo their unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full exactions, and impoſitions. One is as <hi>under the Law,</hi> to them that are <hi>under the Law,</hi> (diſpenſing with a harmeleſſe and decent ceremony) the other rather then indure a ceremony, will let go the Law it ſelf. One is as <hi>without the Law,</hi> to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170560:26"/> them that are <hi>without the Law</hi> (in matters of liberty, and equity) the other is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Law, even to thoſe that are, and would be under the Law. Becauſe (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be with others) he would have no Law over himſelf, but his own will. One is all this, to loſe of himſelf, that he might but <hi>gaine</hi> others: the other is all this, to the loſſe of all others, that he might gaine to himſelf. Now then, how aptly may he admoniſh to moderation; that ſo acted it? But how ſcurvily it founds in all ſuch mens mouthes, as were adverſaries to it? to hear an immoderate man adviſe, or aske for moderation, that never afforded it: or to urge it, that never intended it. Is, as if an Anarchicall Leveller ſhould remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate for a regulated Monarchy: And a rigid Presbyterian ſhould preach for a moderated Epiſcopacy: unles it be to ſerve the Truth, rather then the Time.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The vertue, or thing admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Moderation, which is a vertue of vertues (as I ſaid at firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) And would require not only a whole volume
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170560:27"/> in Morallity, to ſhew how ſhe governs every vertue: but a juſt Treatiſe in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to ſet forth, how ſhe ſerves every grace, and ſeaſons every duty. I ſhall labour to preſent her only as in a Type. For being ſuch a tranſcendent, exactly defined ſhe cannot be. Neither indeed is ſhe to be deſcribed, but according to her equitable and well proportioned circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of things, and perſons, and time, and place.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Hebrew</hi> knowes it by no other name, nor hath a more principle expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, then by that of <hi>Rectitude;</hi> or (plurally altogether) <hi>Rectitudes.</hi> To note, That moderation comprizes in it all kind of directneſſe and uprightneſſe, both in matters naturall, morall, politike, and religious.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Septuagint</hi> make uſe of the word (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) as Gods attribute only: as if creatures were ſcarce capable of it. And that as an attribute of his mercy on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as if Gods mercy were the greateſt moderation of himſelf) in his propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170560:27"/> indulgence, condonation, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, acceptation, &amp;c. For ſo they uſe it in <hi>Pſalme</hi> 86.5. <hi>Ezra.</hi> 8.9. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.22. Even the <hi>Apochrypha</hi> alſo addes it to his juſtice, and judgments. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 12.18. his chaſtenings and corrections. 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 10.4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is ſeverally tranſlated both in the Text, and new Teſtament; <hi>moderation, modeſty, equity, humanity, gentleneſſe, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, courteſie, patience</hi> of Spirit, and <hi>ſoftneſs</hi> of mind. And all theſe ſunani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous rendrings are but to ſignifie, how many qualifications of vertue go to make up this great one of moderation. As mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly, not only in the ſhamefaſt culture, but humble apprehenſion of a mans ſelf. Equity, in caſe of due and right, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to convenience and neceſſity. Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe of Natures; Clemency of Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors; Courteſy of Equalls; Patience in Tryalls; Softneſſe of Inferiors; and Humanity of all, and in all rationall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The antient Fathers (Greek and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170560:28"/> Latine) generally tranſlate it modeſty: and mean it, ſome of a decent demean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of a mans ſelf; ſome of a benigne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting of others actions; but moſtly of a patient tolleration of the Croſſe and perſecution. Inferring hereupon <hi>the Lord is at hand:</hi> ſo to redreſſe and reward all: Among which I may not forget <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> for a tranſlation by himſelf. <hi>Probum veſtrum coram hominibus appareat. Let your honeſty appear before all men.</hi> He ſo ſpeaks in his Book of Formall Culture. And ſpeaks to ſuch women as were careleſſe of their modeſt behaviour before men; upon pretext of the purity of their hearts and intentions to God. To theſe he makes the Apoſtles intent to be this. <hi>Ad quid, niſi ut malitia ad vos acceſſum omnino non habeat; &amp; ut malis &amp; exemplo, &amp; testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio ſitis.</hi> To what end is it? but that the malice of the Devil, the fleſh, and the world may have no acceſſe to you: and and that you may be for an example and a teſtimony to bad, both women, and men. Moderation then is a thing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170560:28"/> very meet, and much becoming all Sexes. It not only prevents the evills of either Sex by it ſelf: but eſpecially the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalls of both Sexes met together.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Criticks alſo in their notation of the name, do conferre ſomething to the ſignification, though not enough to the perfect definition of it. Whether it be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>juſtum,</hi> or of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>cedo,</hi> or of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſimile, conſentaneum conveniens,</hi> put all together, and they help ſomewhat towards the deſcription of it, <hi>viz.</hi> Moderation is that whereby Juſtice departs from her rigour, and a man yields of his right, only to do that which is convenient in equity, conſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous to right reaſon, and decent in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry circumſtance.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Schoolmen and Moraliſts, ſome make it to be a potential part of Juſtice, bringing (not in ſeverity) the fact home to the Law; but rather (in equity) the Law down to the fact. Not ſuffering the Law to be in force againſt any, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her ſelf had a being. And though
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170560:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170560:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170560:30"/> the Law takes upon her to cenſure of no more then the poſtfact, yet even ſo Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration benignly interprets it in ſome favour to the Sufferer, all circumſtances conſidered. It would have every cenſure warne, before it ſtrikes. But above all, it cannot abide the immoderation of ſuch a ſentence, as ſhall exalt and ſet up it ſelf for the preſent, and againſt one: and at the ſame inſtant to repeal and cry down it ſelf for the future, ſo as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern any other. Becauſe it takes Lawes to be intended, not for an execution at once, or upon one: but for a perpetual rule and example to all ſevere penalties, and ſuch as wherein it is hard to obſerve a Moderation or Proportion; it takes them to be (like thoſe of the <hi>Talion</hi> Law) intended rather <hi>in terrorem,</hi> and for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention; then preciſe execution where it ſeems to deſert the ſtrict Letter of the Law, it doth but now appeal to the mind of the Lawgiver, what he himſelf would have done, if the particular caſe had been now brought before him, and whether
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170560:30"/> his Reaſon would not there ſomewhat have ruled the caſe, where it was not poſſible for words ſufficiently to provide? And whether the Law it ſelf was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for ſomewhat indefinite; where examples and contingents are ſo indifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; and ſo often found to fall out? And all this it doth, leaſt <hi>ſummum jus</hi> might become <hi>ſumma injuria.</hi> And that Juſtice her ſelf migh have her commendation for moderative, more then vendicative: as minding rather to amend, then confound. Notwithſtanding all this; though mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration be not curſt, and cruel, like a Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame, in her corrections, but tender, and compaſſionate as a mother: yet is ſhe farre from being over indulgent, remiſſe, diſpenſing, arbitrary, or licentious. Not ſo, as that men ſhould grow immoderate in their vices, and crimes, upon a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of a moderation in the cenſure or penalty. Some again take it for a price, and maſter-peice, of Prudence; wiſely diſcerning betwixt what is juſt, and fitt: and ſo giving ſentence, rather congruouſly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170560:31"/> then ſeverely. Not raſhly, and arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily diſpenſing with the wiſdome of a Law; as if it were no more but a leaden Rule: but circumſpectly and benignly interpreting it, as that it may not prove an Iron Rod. Gravely ſuppoſing that there is a naturall intended equity in every Law (although unwritten) to correct (upon occaſion) the literall written rigour. In as much as a Law intending generall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, cannot be ſo cautiouſly deviſed, and compoſed; as to provide ſufficiently, and conveniently, in caſe of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar accident. And therefore the prudent dictate of right reaſon is often faine to interpoſe, and moderate between the bark and heart of the Law. That the Law being but one, and bound up in Syllables; might abound in its ſenſe; and might juſtly and wiſely apply to the variety of Facts, and their more various circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Moderation is wiſe; and hath her eyes in her head, to look round about her: And ſo likewiſe, wiſdome is moderate, in judging what is neceſſary, what conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170560:31"/> But after the imprudence, nay, and impudence of immoderation, it ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es forward arrogantly and unadviſedly to what it affects, (Like a Horſe in a blind Halter) not ſeeing what is conſiderable on either ſide. Mark an immoderate man; and he never marks what you ſay; becauſe he minds only what he would ſay him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And it hath been obſerved (even in matters of no leſſe importance, then Church, and State (Government) none have been more immoderate, then the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned; or but half-witted at moſt. For byaſſed affecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns have not been aware of any true advertiſements. And ſo they have boldly mott their bolts, without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fear or witt. As we have a Senate: Oh that we had a Synode of moderate men! never till then will prudence play her part, for the peace and truth, both in Church and Common-wealth. But to proceed with the Cardinal vertues. I find moderation is a chief property even of Fortitude alſo. For in the body, it is no more but the ſtrength of a beaſt: it is the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170560:32"/> minde that gives it the moderation of a man. All other things are but the Iron and Ammunition: but this is the Gold, and precious mettle of Fortitude. By thoſe indeed others may be conquered, but by this alone it is, that a man over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes himſelf. A man that is immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in his paſſions, you ſhall always have him either daunted, or deſperate, in the appearance of difficulties, or approach of dangers: what is it but moderation, that makes the true temper, betwixt a puſila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous fear, and an over-confident au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacity? what are all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aggreſtions of Fortitude, but over-dareings; and all the perpeſtions of it, but under-ſhrinkings; if moderation be a way? And how comes in that Heroick Spirit <hi>(our Royal Martyr)</hi> with his Motto of <hi>more then Conquerour,</hi> Who left nothing of moderation unat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted: who ſet upon nothing of force but to which he was forced and neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Who laboured to have made his Religion, and reaſon, and Lawes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170560:32"/> more then his Armes, who ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prevent or remove all difficulties; although they were not occaſional only, but contrived. Who lookt upon dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as others more then his own. All whoſe feares were for nothing more then the common miſery, who ſtrove alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to be on the defenſive, and not on the offenſive part, who did all theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and honourable things, that ought to be done: before he ſuffered theſe more then diſhonourable and diſhoneſt evils, that muſt be ſuffered, who lookt death (to mortals th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> utmoſt of terribles) clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the face, bold as a Lion, while the Foxes and Tygres ſtood by trembling and amazed, both covering their faces and hanging down their heads. In a word, who left his Empire with more true courage and valour, then all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies could uſurp it. After ſo great a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of magnanimous patience: there's no telling of our Sequeſtrations, Decimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Confiſcations, Impriſonments, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, Mancipations, Mutilations
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170560:33"/> Murders, Deaths: no, though peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it might be ſaid we moderated our ſelves to ſuffer them, with courage and conſtancy too in our kind. Laſtly, as for Temperance, who but the ſenſual are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible that the All of it is in Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It were long to ſpeak of the immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate luxurie and voluptuouſneſſe, in meats, drink<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, apparel, and other carnal pleaſures, and vaine delectations; which they of every Sex, Age, and Degree, had given themſelves up unto. And they not only our oppreſſors, who had engroſſed to themſelves the fat of the land, and lived to no other purpoſe, but to ſuck the ſweet of it. But they alſo, who have no other wayes to ſweeten their oppreſſion, but by helping to devoure their own honey; ſince the robbers had entred the Hive, making this their only contentment to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the time in all the vanity of it, for all the miſery of it; even theſe men alſo ſeem to me (whether they live in Warre or Peace) to be borne to no other end but conſume fruits. Of theſe therefore I ſay,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170560:33"/> It wil be hard to find moderate men to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that are immoderate in ſenſe. Neither are ſuch men fit to be conſulted about the publick health and ſoundneſſe, that have addicted themſelves to ſpend their own days, in a continual ſickneſs and diſtemper. Who but diſpenſing <hi>Epicures</hi> (though pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending <hi>Stoicks</hi>)(men of decoited patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, or of deſperate and deſpicable for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes) were the authors of all our diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? <hi>(whoſe God is their belly, and whoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is in their ſhame) Phil.</hi> 3.19. And there is no greater care of any, then of ſuch, to laviſh and ſquander away our hopefull peace and proſperity again.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Thus hath Moderation entred the nature and definition of all the foure Cardinal Vertues, (Juſtice, Prudence, Fortitude, and Temperance) And if I ſhould now ſpeak of the three Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical graces, (Faith, Hope, and Charity) Moderation comes in to the deſcription or true conſiſtency of them all. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt them from this, and Faith eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generates either into credulity, or infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170560:34"/> Hope into Preſumption or Deſpair: and Love into hatred or vile affection: yea, and all Religion, either into Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition or Profanation. Let the Grace or the Duty be never ſo good and holy: yet Moderation is well-buſied to the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of them. Though not in their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute nature, (peradventure) and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet in their beſt convenience, and in every meet circumſtance, that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne or adorne them. And ſo is no allay even to the higheſt Powers of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and operation of Gods Spirit, but is the very height and eminency of all ſuch devout exerciſes, as amount to no more but a reaſonable ſervice of him. Yea, even in the deepeſt myſteries, it is a being wiſe unto ſobrietie; and in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward practice, a being wiſe unto ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: tending only to order and edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them both.</p>
               <p n="8">8. As it is the ſalt, or diſcreet ſeaſoning of things ſpiritual. So it is the ſoul and vigorous life of things adiaphorous. Nay, it changes their very nature, converting
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170560:34"/> them into that of its own. For it is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration that makes indifferent things good: as it is immoderation that makes them bad. It is the whole ſubſtance, in a matter of circumſtance. Yea, it is the rule and Canon, in all Rites and Ceremonies. Since our breaches and irregularities ſeemed at firſt to burſt forth about Rites and Ceremonies eccleſiaſticall (and they ſo immoderately rejected, upon pretence they were immoderately impoſed) let me here ſpeak as a moderate man, to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate men. All actions (humane, or divine, private or publick) muſt neceſſarily be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſome circumſtances. In the humane, and private, every private man hath his liberty: in the divine, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, every publick man ought to obſerve his order. And whether is it not juſt and meet, that the publick ſhould be of a publick choyce, and determination? with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion, it belongs peculiarly to the eccleſiaſticall politie to have her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and authority, for the making of her Canons and Tenets about externall
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170560:35"/> and indifferent matters. To which liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church, every private mans li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty ought to ſubſcribe, even for the authorities falle. If ſuch things retayn but their middle nature, and no more; what now ſhould hinder a conſcience (informed and guided according to the dictates of right reaſon) from aſſenting, and ſubſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? eſpecially, when they neither labor, nor ſavour of impiety, idolatry, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, inſignification, burdenſomeneſſe, lightneſſe, nor profaneneſſe: but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, are moderate, decent, ſolemne, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout, adorning and edifying. Though Rites and Ceremonies eccleſiaſtical be not accounted ſimply as parts of divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; nor to have an internal ſanctity in them: yet are they not without their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal integrity and beauty; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be reckoned of as ſacred appendices ornaments, and adjuments at leaſt. Whereby the Church is rendred more reverential, and eſtimable, not only to thoſe that are within, but alſo to thoſe that are without. It may here be diſtinguiſhed
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170560:35"/> betwixt Rites, and Ceremonies Divine, and Humane. Thoſe that are purely Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, are univerſally to be retained of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. Such as are theſe which formally concern the Sacraments in their inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The meerly humane are not to be admitted, if they come with an auſtere impoſition, and ſtrickt obligation upon conſcience, as neceſſarily tending to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and yet having no more ground for all, but tradition only. Nevertheleſs, the eccleſiaſticall, as they are not to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed as purely Divine: ſo are they not to be accounted of as meerly Humane. For they are the order and harmony of Religion; the guide and help to devotion, and have ſomething conſonant to Gods Word even in this, that they have nothing repugnant to it. If then there be nothing in them directly againſt Faith, Reaſon, or good Manners, but that they may conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently ſerve for uniformity, and conſent, for exhortation, and incitation: they are not only to be not reproved nor oppoſed by any; but being lawfully inſtituted, or
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170560:36"/> by being an innocent cuſtome received, they ought rather to be praiſed, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by all. And therefore they rather are to be reproved, who do account it their ſingular praiſe, and as it were part of their private authority; to reject or alter, antient and harmleſſe uſes and cuſtoms: whether it be becauſe they would have all ſuch to be utterly neglected; or becauſe they would have ſome of their own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies or inventions, to be introduced and imbraced in their ſtead. Although ſuch Rites be not to be eſtimated, as of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right; perpetuall, immutable, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, efficacious; as the Word, Faith, and Doctrine it ſelf. Yet antient and wel ſetled Ceremonies (not ſuperfluous, nor defective; but comely and uſefull) are not to be changed, upon a pretext, no, nor upon every probability of ſomthing more profitable. Becauſe all the benefit may be ſuch as may not countervaile the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and damage of the innovation. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in all ſuch as are of a ſober and ſetled uſe; it is temerarious to ſeek, or work
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170560:36"/> their alteration; and it be for no more but the peace and unities ſake. If at any time an alteration or aboliſhing of them (or any of them) be thought either neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, or convenient; it ought to be the act of the whole Church in her repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative, not neglecting her alſo in her dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſive capacity. But a thing of ſo much conſequence, ought not to be uſurped by every private man, in his private place. This is the buſineſſe, not of the Miniſtry alone, nor of the Magiſtrates alone: It properly belongs to a Synode (rightly convened) and a Senate, to decree, and effect it; by their prudent and mature conſultation, and conſent. Nor are they ſo much to reſpect the factions, or ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, petitions, complaynts, remonſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, objections, importunities, or tumults, of Recuſants, Sectaries, Schiſmaticks, Fanaticks, Separatiſts, or Singulariſts. Becauſe they that turbulently, or peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſe the Church in her order, and peace; will conſequently (nay, peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do it purpoſely) to oppugne her in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170560:37"/> ſound Doctrine, and intire profeſſion. But of late have we had the ſad and ſhamefull experience, how the over-heady exploding of our Diſcipline hath ſiniſterly proved to the much proſtituting, and almoſt profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating of our Doctrine; and that by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſmes, mere lyes, and blaſphemies, horrible to be uttered unto Chriſtian ears. If it may not be otherwiſe perſwaded, or ruled (by all that moderation can do) ſomething of indifferency may be yeilded or remitted, or permited (as then it was) during the impetuouſneſſe of ſuch head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong violence and extremity. But all immoderation is to be examined, now that (by Gods good and wiſe providence) moderation is come in place. Clamour is not now to prevaile, but reaſon. Nor are immoderate affectations to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but moderate affections. Every pretext or cry of Chriſtian liberty, or weake conſcience, is not preſently to be accepted for ſuch indeed, as it doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. The property whereof, is to be more willing to hear, then earneſt to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170560:37"/> object; to be readier to depoſe it ſelf, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then plead only for its diſpenſation; to look at, and labor to acquieſſe in others ſatisfaction, as well as its own. Somthing (when they are found to be ſuch) may be indulged to weak Brethren, but nothing to falſe Brethren. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.4. and 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. If they be but things indifferent, why then ſhould not a man be as equall for their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, as for their refuſall? nay, why not for their reception rather; when mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration hath made them good, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority lawfull? They may be ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly abuſed, and ſo they may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely neglected. There may be a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity of them to ſcandall and offence: So there may be a deficiency of them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, and confuſion. Theſe things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may not ſimply approve our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences to God: but by theſe things we may commend our ſelves to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point; though uniformity be no abſolute note of the Catholick
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170560:38"/> Church: yet ſuch Canons and Rites, as have been decreed in generall free Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, are to be preferred before thoſe that are conſtituted in this or that particular Church. Albeit theſe are to be obſerved, rather then thoſe: becauſe it is neither neceſſary, nor poſſible to bring the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church (whoſe unity is that of the Word and Spirit) to our uniformity. Hence it is a hatefull thing, for particular Churches to make compariſons in matter of this Nature: Or for theſe things to be undervaluing, or invective one againſt another. Moſt of all for one Church ſo to arrogate, as to ſeek to reduce and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme another herein to it ſelf. Becauſe it is to be charitably ſuppoſed, that every Church hath good cauſe and reaſon for thoſe of its own. To which every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of it is bound in conſcience to ſubmit, and conforme. Yea, a member of one nationall Church ſojourning in another, is not now obliged to the Rites of his own Church: but (to avoyd ſcandal, and for unities ſake) ought rather to apply
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170560:38"/> himſelf to the laudable uſes of the preſent place. How odious is it then, for one of the ſame Church, to take upon him to propound, and promote the cuſtomes and uſages of another Church; before thoſe of his own? This (in a moderate way) have I ſaid for Ceremony. Much more might eaſily be ſaid of Epiſcopacy, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, holy Feſtivalls, ſacred Temples, Muſick in Churches. Canonicall houres, Decent Veſtures, and Geſtures, Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall goods and Tythes. (In moſt of all which there is ſomething more then Adiaphorous;) though nothing more then requires moderation: albeit much to the confutation of immoderate men. But rather then to check at theſe immoderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or propound a moderation in theſe particulars; I will here wait (with all moderate men) to accept it from a Synod moſt willingly. Which the Lord (for Chriſt ſake) ſend us! even a reverend, and bleſſed Synod, of moderate men.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Beſides what moderation hath plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeared to be in it ſelf: it is not a little
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170560:39"/> illuſtrated from its contrary, immodera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which is nothing elſe but an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream vitiouſneſſe of Perſons, in their judgments, opinions, paſſions, affections, actions, manners, pretences, and deſigns. Of all which we are not ſo pathetically apprehenſive in the qualities, as in the effects. What was it but immoderation? that turned Epiſcopacy into Presbytery, Presbytery into Independency; Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency into Anabaptiſme; Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme into Quakeriſme; and Quakeriſme almoſt unto all kind of Jeſuitiſme? That turned Religion into policy; Reformation into Innovation; Profeſſion into Pretence, That turned Miniſters into Souldiers; and Souldiers into Preachers; Prophets into Prognoſticators; Churches into Stables; Pallaces and Collegiate places into Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns and Ale-houſes; Cathedralls into private habitations; Church-Organs into Tavern-Muſick. That turned Parliaments into Juntoes; Parliamentary edicts into military remonſtrances; The Counſel of State into a Counſel of Warre; and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170560:39"/> Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy into Covenants and Engagements; Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Laws into arbitrary impoſitions and exactions. That turned Liberty into Licentiouſneſſe; Order into Confuſion; Government into Tyranny; Freedom into Slavery; Propriety into Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Degrees into Parity; Plenty into Poverty; Peace into Warre; Security and Safety into Jealouſies and Fears. That turned Courts of known Law, into an High Court of unknown Juſtice; and laſtly (ſo it could go no further) Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pallity into Protectorſhip, and all loyall Subjection into moſt horrid parricidall, regicidall Aſſaſſination.</p>
               <p n="10">10. After all this upon Moderation at large I have yet once more to take a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower veiw of it, as it is deſcribed in my Text. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>That Moderate thing.</hi> The Adjective neuter put Subſtantively, or the concrete in ſtead of the abſtract. May not this emphaticall forme of ſpeaking be to note the quality of moderation inveſted with all its acts, and circumſtances, for
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170560:40"/> take moderation in the abſtract meerly, as a naked quality, diſpoſition, or habit; and however it may even ſo affect a man within himſelf, yet it affects little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in others. Or that, be it never ſo faire or moderately contrived, and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for the manner of it, yet all this is nothing to manifeſt a moderation, if the matter or thing it ſelf be immoderate. Or that moderation (as all other Graces and Vertues) are to be commended and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled in the abſtract: but admoniſhed and commended in the concrete. Becauſe the quality is for applauſe: but the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice for exhortation. Or, would he thus preferr ſome one moderate thing before another? For there is a meliority, and a putiority in things of moderation. Or would he not thus bring every thing, though not to one meaſure, yet to one nature of moderation? For true mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is but one thing in all things. I reſt with this thought, that the Apoſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is the ſame reciprocally with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. which is the conveniences and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170560:40"/> behovefulneſſe of all actions, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions (which our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf had reſpect unto in all his) <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.5. and 2.10. and 7.26. and is required in all his Saints. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.10. 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 11.13.) For whatſoever is meet, is moderate and whatſoever is moderate, is meer. And ſo it amounts to as much as the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.35. <hi>That which is comely,</hi> which hath with it there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly the juſt bounds of moderation: that is to ſay, when neither the Impoſer <hi>caſts a ſnare,</hi> nor the Submitter is <hi>diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> in his Duty. And ſo (on Gods name) <hi>let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Appropriation, or Subject to which the Admonition relates, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>your Moderation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Yours primely, and chiefly, let your moderation firſt be known to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; yea, though their moderation be not known to you: that ſo theirs may
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170560:41"/> come to be known to you at laſt. But firſt yours, and then theirs, Alwayes in the way of Moderation, ſome (and they chief ones) muſt firſt begin, that ſo the reſt may follow after, Admonition may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure much perſwade it: but ti is example that moſt induces to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of it. I hear many ſay, would God things were well and handſomely moderated amongſt us. But all proves but a vaine and fruitleſſe wiſh, while no man begins to go about it: In this therefore we are all to be diſpraiſed, that we ſloathfully leave the praiſe to others, to ſit upon it. Notwithſtanding we are all ready enough to own it to our ſelves: that is, to challenge it, rather then to attempt it, which is as much as each man exacting anothers moderation, but no man exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting his own. How eager are that ſort of men now to claime it, that did ſo furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſclaime it heretofore. Moderation is with them now a favourable diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which before was nothing elſe but a cold lukewarmeneſſe, or a deteſtable
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170560:41"/> neutrallity. While their fiery zeal burned, we heard no other, but curſe ye <hi>Meroz,</hi> becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord againſt the Mighty: curſed be he that doth the work of the Lord negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; curſed be he that keepeth back his Sword from blood.—down with it, down with it even to the ground.—cut it off root and branch—with hundreds of ſuch like abuſive fumes and flames. But now (that God be thanked) he hath quencht their thornes; they begin to call for poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> to dip the tip of his finger in water to coole their tongues, &amp;c. Though I wonder, with what face or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence they can ask that, which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves would not afford: or preſume to obtaine that to themſelves, which they denyed to others: Nevertheleſſe, I wiſh with all my heart, they may find mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in all her bowells (ſo they would not prove Snakes in her boſome) that ſo ſhe may heap coals (in the beſt ſenſe) upon their heads.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yours perſonally. For moderation
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170560:42"/> is of Perſons, before things. They are our paſſions and affections that firſt ask mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating: and then nothing can be done by us immoderately; nothing can ſeem ſo to us, that is not ſimply evill. Had we but this <hi>Salt in our ſelves,</hi> we ſhould ſoon have <hi>peace one with another. Mark.</hi> 9.50. For it is impoſſible he ſhould be unſavoury without, that is ſo well ſeaſoned within. Mark, how men diſpute, diſcourſe, preach, pray, plead, nay clamor about Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: when all the immoderation is in themſelves only. Such and ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to have Courts, Offices, Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Diſcipline, yea, Prerogatives, Priviledges, Liberties, &amp;c. regulated ſo and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o: and yet (would they examine themſelves, and others diſcerne them) there is nothing needs more regulation then their own judgments, opinions, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, affections, humours, fancies; affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. O man! do but moderate thy ſelf, and all things elſe are ſoon made ſo unto thee.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yours plurally, A ſingle moderate
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170560:42"/> man can only ſatisfie, and ſedate himſelf, but no more. And the moderation of a few avayles little; eſpecially where the moderate party is out voted by the immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate. This, (oh this!) is to be lookt upon, and lamented as the ſpring, the ſtream, and the Sea of all our immodera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The Lord increaſe the numbers, and meaſures of moderate minded men! for the peace of the Church, for the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of the Land, the honour of the King, and the glory of his holy Name.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yours properly, as Chriſtians and not as moralliſts only. To read ſo much of moderation in morallity; and to find ſo little application made of it in Divinity; would make one think it to be their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and not ours. But that the Miſtriſs might not borrow of her handmaid; St. <hi>Paul</hi> firſt obſerved it on <hi>Christ:</hi> and ſo, as Chriſtians, appropriated it unto us. If therefore we obſerved or conſider it in our ſelves as we ought; our moderation hath theſe Prerogatives to theirs. Firſt, theirs had no more but meer men for their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples; ours hath for its patte n the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170560:43"/> Son of God himſelf. Next, theirs had but only the Rule of Reaſon to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate it ſelf by: ours beſides the moral Law of God, hath alſo the Law of faith. Again, theirs was to governe inordinate paſſions, affections and appetites as vices to nature: ours, as ſinnes againſt God. Again, theirs rended to moderate a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick only, but ours the Church alſo. And again, their paſſive moderation was to die like Stoicks: but ours like Martyrs. Laſtly, theirs lookt no further then men and mortallity, but ours at God and eternity. Now though their moral vertues needed thoſe moderations, which our ſpiritual graces ſimply do not, brings the more immediate, and ſpeciall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Spirit. In which there is no fear of exceſſe, and from which theres no danger of an utter defect. Yet for all that, our exerciſes of them want mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration very often: becauſe if not through our contrary corruptions; yet through manifold emulations, and indiſcretions; they are too ſubject to either extream.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170560:43"/> Now God grant, that morall men may not excell us in moderation! leaſt ſo their morall vertues may take ſcandall; and have cauſe to call our ſpirituall graces into queſtion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Yours collectively; as a Church. For the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks it to the whole Church of the <hi>Philippians.</hi> The mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating of a Perſon, is much; but of a Church or Congregation, much more. Becauſe, it is alwaies harder to bring a multiplicity of Spirits, unto the unity of the Spirit. Oh this Church moderation! that indeed is to be labored for above all. For the Common-wealth can never be moderate, where the Church is not firſt ſo. What but immoderate conciliables, and conventicles, have hatched, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented all our immoderations? And now theres no hope or likely-hood, out of a moderate Senate, and a moderate Synod, to allay them. And this we hope in God they wi l do: becauſe the Lord is there at hand. At hand to moderate, at hand to help, and bleſſe their moderation.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170560:44"/>6. Yours preciſely; as of the ſame particular Church, and eſpecially among, and within your ſelves. For though all Churches ought to be moderate, and ought to remark and conſider the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all Churches: yea, and one Church is bound to make known her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to all Churches. Nevertheleſs, our moderation is not neceſſary to all Churches, in every matter. Becauſe (all things well weighed in their cauſes, or circumſtances) this, or that thing may be moderate to this, or that Church; which to another may ſeem, or prove immoderate. Surely then theſe men muſt needs be very immoderate, that cannot content themſelves within themſelves; but muſt ſeek to moderate or modell, to reforme or conforme, one Church to all Churches; or all. Churches to one Church. How incongruous is ſuch a thing, and abſurd? Eſpecially when it is of the more famous, and renowned; to the more ſlender, and obſcure. We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt (and not unworthily) the uſurpation
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170560:44"/> of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; in that ſhe ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogantly preſumes to reduce into her communion, all Churches, by an unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of diſcipline, as well as doctrine. And ſhall we deviſe, or endeavour ſo farr forth in her invitation, as to make another proud Catholick, of a poor particular Church? God forbid.</p>
               <p>Thus farr of the appropriation here, or relation to our Subject. Now give me leave to take all the Subjects of it along; as I find them elſe-where. Whereof the moſt eminent is</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Now I Paul my ſelf beſeech you by the meekneſſe, and gentleneſſe, or moderation of Chriſt.</hi> Loe here Chriſtians! moderation is Chriſts own attribute. Whoſe Perſon was a moderation, betwixt a God, and a man; whoſe actions were a moderation, tempering graciouſly betwixt his great perfections, and our no leſſe infirmities; whoſe paſſion was a moderation, ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170560:45"/> the Juſtice, and meriting the Divine mercy both at once. But we are chiefly to conſider, what uſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here makes of it. Though he makes here a tripple propounding of his own perſon, yet it is not as a perfect patterne of moderation; he leaves that to <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone. Yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he doth it to ſingle out himſelf from ſome others. And indeed, though we all may admoniſh to moderation; yet no man is ſo fit to adjure others thereunto, as he that is of a ſingular eminence therein. Some have conceived him to ſpeak here ironically; ſpeaking now to falſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and their Followers. And verily, a man ſcarce knows how to ſpeak to ſuch of moderation, and ſpeak in good earneſt. They may well be taunted and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the beſt mens moderation: For they will never be intreated, or reduced to it, no not in an ordinary way. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeches them, but he ſays not what. For they that will not be intreated by mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, a man may ſpare the reſt, becauſe they will be perſwaded by nothing at all
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170560:45"/> that good is. It was upon ſome immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of theirs, whereupon he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to challenge them by this. And that was a deſpicable eſtimation, firſt of his Perſon, then of his Office, and laſtly of his Doctrine. And this was the very immoderation of them with us; Oh this was theirs altogether! I need ſay no more. But theſe had a fond conceit or preſumption of his being more meek and moderate in preſence, then in abſence. Juſt ſo it was with one (of bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) who while he was in preſence, they preſumed him eaſie, and ſoft, and mild (and that moderation was his only immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration) but in abſence, they found him wiſe and bold, (not only beyond their expectation, but to their admiration) And this (even this) was the maine reaſon why they durſt not indure to hear of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence any more. But notwithſtanding all this, the Apoſtle conjures theſe falſe Teachers, and their followers by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of Chriſt. And ſo will I do ours. Now I beſeech you by the moderation
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170560:46"/> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (by which your ſins muſt be pardoned, and your Souls ſaved) learne moderation yet at length: and if you will not be Friends with it, yet be not Enemies to it: deſpiſeing, dominion, and ſpeaking evill of dignities, on the one ſide: and having mens perſons in admiration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of advantage, on the other.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Miniſters. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. For ſuch an one ought to be, <hi>not greedy of filthy lucre, but patient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r moderate,</hi> Why ſuch an affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative inforced upon ſuch a negative? but to teach, That Miniſters (and others alſo) had yet been moderate in their opinions; had they not firſt bin immoderate in their covetouſneſſe, what elſe was it, but a greedy aime at their great livings, which cauſed them to convent (nay, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent) ſo many for ſcandalous Miniſters, and Malignants? But the next word to it is alſo to be taken notice of, <hi>Moderate, not a Brawler.</hi> (Not quarrelling whether with tongue or fiſt. But if like i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſtrickt originall, (unfighting) which puts
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170560:46"/> it into my thoughts, that if Miniſters had not been ſo immoderate as to turne Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: Souldiers had never been ſo immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate as to turne preachers. There was a ſcandalous report of a Miniſter ſo tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly pugnacious, as to take that fatall Axe in hand, and doe that diabolical ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution. Which if it had been ſo, the Papiſts might have boaſted, ſuch helliſh King-killing Inſtruments were to be found amongſt others alſo; as well as among their own Prieſts, and Jeſuits. But Brethren of the Cleargy! you know moderation is among the moſt excellent of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial endowments. Now by the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Chriſt I beſeech you, (in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of diſcipline, order, uniformity) let it not be ſaid, A Miniſter, and nor mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All Chriſtians. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Gentle or moderate.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. <hi>The good, and gentle, or moderate.</hi> The places ſpeak it of all Chriſtians, of all ſexes, ages, degrees, callings, conditions. For it is Moderation (the univerſal vertue) that be fits and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes them all.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170560:47"/>4. Morall men, and Heathens. <hi>Act.</hi> 24.4. —<hi>Hear us of thy clemency, or modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> It was there the apologetick com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of a Heathen Oratour to a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Governour. However, it ſerves to let us obſerve, that moderation was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and expected even among Heathens, and that not in their perſons only, but in their places alſo. Now then, what a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſhame were it, that we ſhould be driven to ſuſpect it, or bidden to deſpaire of it, in the perſons, or places, of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſors.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Manifeſtation <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Let it be known;</hi> Thus namely,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Simply apparent in it ſelf. He doth not ſay, make them to know it. As he uſes a word of neer kinne, in the next verſe, to ſignify ſo much. <hi>Let your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts be made known,</hi> &amp;c. For in truth it is an eaſier thing to make our requeſts known to God: then to make our mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration known to men. And becauſe the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170560:47"/> Apoſtle puts theſe two evident things of our ſelves (to God, and men) ſo neer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; it learnes us, that no man can rightly make his prayers known to God, that neglects to let his moderation be known to men. For even while he is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering his gift at the Altar, he may there be convinc't to remember, that his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ſomething againſt him in this defect. But if a man want this moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on within himſelf. Lord, what prayers doth he make? Surely, he is like one of thoſe immoderate Suiters to whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>ye know not what ye ask:</hi> or rather like one of thoſe, of whon St. <hi>James</hi> ſaid, <hi>ye ask and receive not, becauſe ye ask a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, that ye may conſume it upon your luſts.</hi> Or elſe he <hi>kills and deſires;</hi> in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate, uncharitable, envious, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengfull prayers. Or he asks not in Faith, nothing wavering, &amp;c. Or he firſt ſeeks not the Kingdome of God, &amp;c. Or he cryed not to God in his heart, when he howled upon his Bed. Or he prayed to be ſeen of men. Or he uſed vaine
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170560:48"/> repetitions, thinking to be heard for his much babling. This minds me to put thoſe men in mind of their inordinate prayers; who prayed, not in their immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration only, but for their immoderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alſo. But to proceed upon my firſt hint; It is ſufficient, if moderation be known, or evident to be ſuch in it ſelf: whether all, or every one will conceive it to be ſo; yea or no. For if ſhe had no more evidence, and demonſtration in her ſelf, but what ſhe muſt be glad to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or obtaine from all, or every mans apprehenſion and opinion of her: One man would fancy her to be one thing: and another to be another: and ſo ſhe ſhould be nothing at the laſt. Whereas (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will conceive it ſo, or no) that indeed is moderation, that ſatisfies the beſt reaſons, and ſuits with the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, although it be not anſwerable to ſome mens opinions; yea or (for the preſent) may be to ſome mens particular inconveniences.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Known really, to be very modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170560:48"/> it ſelf, and no other: the ſame and not the contrary. Not auſterity, rigidneſs, inexorableneſſe, impoſition, compulſion, on the one hand: nor yet remiſneſſe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, connivence, arbitraryneſſe, or licentiouſneſſe, on the other. But a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle kind of equity, indulgency, benignity, betwixt both extreamities. Men over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrickt and nice; yea, and men very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and looſe; neither of them will know moderation to be as it is: but rather, as either of them have a mind to make it to themſelves. And betwixt them both, it never ſcapes the imputation or calumny, either of a ſuperſtitious reſtriction; or of a profane relaxation. And (which is ſtrange) the ſtrict man thinks it too ſtrict for his liberty: and the licentious man thinks it not remiſſe enough to his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiniſme.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Known plainly and ſincerely: not pretended, or diſſembled; not vaunted or boaſted. For if it be either inſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or oſtentation, neither of theſe can make a true manifeſtation of it. Becauſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170560:49"/> one makes it appear to be what it is not: the other would make it appear to be more then it is. Over-backward men, and likewiſe ſuch as are too forward; neither of theſe are the true propalatours, but even both of them (what through feare, or flattery) are but the pretenders to it. One ſort of them are too ſlack to promote it: and the other are ſo haſtily anticipate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they even prevent it. But there is no ſuch pretext or counterfeiting of moderation as when the falſe is borne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, in ſtead of the true. I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that a ſeeming moderation, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure a preſumption of that which was true, upon falſe grounds; hath been the cauſe of all our immoderations: and in the Church more eſpecially. As name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a pretending to reformation, and yet an innovation intended. A conceit of the neceſſity, or perhaps but the expedience, of conforming one Church to another, in circumſtances and externall matters. An affectation of conn'd phraſes and garbes, as a token of unity, and concord. An
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170560:49"/> expectation, yea and a gloriation of the Enthuſiaſtick motions of the Spirit; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, beyond, yea, and againſt the word. An unneceſſary ſcruple of Faith not to be compelled. An abuſive arrogation of that they call Chriſtian liberty: And a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick toleration of all kinds of Sects. And thus indeed while we would feigne our ſelves to be moderate, we fall into all manner of immoderations.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Known; poſitively ſo determined, and declared; not queſtioned, not diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſcepticall way. Moderation, albeit it offers it ſelf to the ſober and ſolid diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſings of reaſon: yet it cannot indure the ſtubborn, or peeviſh tergiverſations of opinion. Nothing makes more againſt it, then when men meet, not like Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, to moderate; but like Antagoniſts, to controvert; nay, and like Adverſaries, to contend. I wonder, how ſhall other queſtions be moderated, if moderation it ſelf be the thing called in queſtion? when it is not admitted in any controverſie, it is the itch: but if ſhe her ſelf come to be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170560:50"/> cavil'd at, it is the ſcab of diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Known effectually; not meerly known, and no more but known; As if all were but barely to propound it to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans indifferent judgment; and ſo leave it to every mans arbitrary proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Why doth the <hi>Apostle</hi> exhort and admoniſh to make it known? if that the very making known, had not fully in it th force of admonition, and exhortation? No doubt, the promulgation or Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, was not without the vertue of the authority, and of the obligation alſo. Becauſe in vain were it known, if it were not to be obſerved, and imitated by all that knew it. What, Friends, I beſeech you! Is this all that you call moderation (or that you underſtand in the way of it?) a thing only to be known; not done? To propoſe ſomething, and yet impoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, though never ſo neceſſary, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient? Ye would make an indulgent Law of it indeed; that muſt only give you leave to give Laws unto your ſelves.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170560:50"/> Nay, and to make your ſelves the Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours of moderation it ſelf. Oh let your moderation be known (even yours) yet at length! As well by receiving the Rules of it from others (eſpecially your Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors) as in giving Rules of it either to your ſelves, or others. Are you ignorant? Moderation will bear with it, till you be inſtructed. Are you erronious? be not immoderate, and you will more eaſily be rectified concerning your Errours. Are you ſcrupulous? Moderation will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerate you, and labour with you for the depoſing of thoſe needleſſe ſcruples. Are you weak, truly weak? Moderation wil plead to a diſpenſing with your weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſo you your ſelves plead not too immoderately to have your weakneſſe only diſpenſt withall. Intending only to reteine it, ſuch as it is, and hug your ſelves in it: not careing, nay, not abiding to be either informed or conformed. But are you factious? what hope can their be of any moderation from you? what help of it to you? Oh the forlorneneſſe of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170560:51"/> this inconſiſtency! It were not Faction, nor would not be, if it were not immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. Are you frowardly cavilling and wrangling? Moderation will confute and convince you though ſhe cannot appeaſe and ſedate you. Are you ſubtile and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling your ſelves for the preſent? Moderation may permit you, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture (for the time) connive at you: but ſhe cannot approve you, not applaud you, not repoſe in you. Laſtly, are you ſchiſmatically and ſeditiouſly turbulent and pernicious? Moderation muſt now (of neceſſity) look about her, leaſt you ſpoile her of all ſhe can call her ſelf, and of all that can come of her. And muſt be forced to let you know and feel, ſhe hath as her tender remiſſions for her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite coertions.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Known throughly and compleatly, to Faith, Conſcience, Reaſon, Senſe. For to appear faire and open in one thing, (a meane one) and to act covertly and cunningly in another, (and that the main) This is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: not a
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170560:51"/> ſingle-hearted equity, but a diſſembled and double-hearted iniquity. But immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is this veteratory hypocrite, which can even ſooth and dandle a man in things of leſſe moment: the rather to enſnare and enſlave them in matters much worſe. We have heretofore beheld with regret, how verſatilely and verſutiouſly ſhe hath plaid her part, betwixt rigour and remiſſeneſſe upon one or other. And how with ſounds of liberty, ſhe would have lull'd us aſleep in our ſlavery. But God be thanked, her Comi-Tragedy is done, and her Actors hiſſ't off the Stage; yea, her nailes are not only pared, but her hood alſo is pull'd off, to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiving of many well-meaning people, who were partly perſwaded by the paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sepulchres, ſpecious glitterings; and could not ſuſpect that noiſome rottenneſs that was within, till they alſo had ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their learning, and that their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible experience had beaten them off the ſoundneſſe of their faith. But this veile of immoderation done away) we all
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170560:52"/> may now behold with open face, how Moderation (that Princely vertue) is come imperfectly to appear what ſhe is; and to manifeſt her ſelf to all others (that will not be blind) according to their ſeveral faculties and capacities. As to be known to faith in things of faith; and to conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in things of conſcience; and to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in things of Reaſon; and even to ſenſe in things of ſenſe. What more then this remains, either for Moderation it ſelfe to do, or for all moderate men to deſire? How extreamly then ſhould they divert, and (as it were) wyer-draw her, that would hale her up to the doctrine of Faith, when ſhe is now only about whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Diſcipline. Or that would drag her down to every pettiſh and petty ſcruple; when ſhe is now upon things, firſt of hers, then of their Chriſtian liberty. But to object irrationally againſt her reaſon, or to be ſenſleſſely refractory to her ſenſe. This is to be exploded as altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Known multiplicitely. For as there
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170560:52"/> is no exerciſe of grace and vertue that ought to be more univerſally notable in the Church of Chriſt then Moderation: ſo none hath more apt and eminent ways of making it ſelf known. By the quality or habit ſo it is to be known to our ſelvs: but it is the <hi>moderate thing,</hi> or act, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it muſt be made known to others. To others made known exactly, ere it can be exacted and importuned from others. Actively made known in affection and diſcretion: paſſively known, by appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and acceptance. Known in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, prayers, profeſſion, diſputation, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour, converſation. Known by ſight and experience, by hearing and good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. Known ſo as communicative, not in groſt. For of a hid treaſure there is no benefit, even our perſonal moderation is to be imparted; but our official much more. Known ſo as now evidenced, but attained long before. For alwayes it is to be ſuppoſed, where there is grace in ſome meaſure, there alſo is Moderation in ſome degree, becauſe Moderation
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170560:53"/> comes along with reaſon, but much more with grace. Made known ſo palpably as that it may be paſt all ſuſpicion. For in truth we are moſtly affected ſo immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately our ſelves, that it is not an eaſie matter to perſwade us thoroughly of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers moderation. Known, to ſtirre up o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to moderation, at leaſt to prevent the contrary in them. Known to Gods glory, the Churches peace, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths proſperity, one anothers edification, and every mans own praiſe. In a word, Moderation is that by which all other vertues are made known to be ſuch: what vertue then is required to the making known of it ſelf?</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Extent, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>unto all men.</hi> Men, and men univerſally, are the objects of our Moderation, of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Nation, Sexe, Age, Degree, Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Condition they be.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Jewes and Gentiles, ſo was the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle moderate towards both, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170560:53"/> both, for the gaining of both, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.20, 21. But by our immodera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we loſe both them and our ſelves to boot. What Jew will convert to that Church, that is diſtracted about harmleſs and convenient ceremonies? That will have all ceremonial diſcipline and order extirpated, under a colour of their cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Lawes abrogation. St. <hi>Paul</hi> would diſpenſe even with their legal rites, that ſo he might winne them to the ſubſtance of the Goſpel; and ſhall we loſe this ſubſtance both to them and to our ſelves, in contending about the ſhadow? This is not the way to promote them to jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and emulation; but to intruſion ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and commixtion. As it was too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of late, when they propoſed to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe our Churches, and petitioned to ſet up their Syn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gogues amongſt us; and not a few of our own Chriſtians, (as a ſcandal no doubt of our immoderate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions) turn'd Jews. What Gentile (that favours any thing of true morality) would convert to that Church, in which
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170560:54"/> he can perceive little or nothing of a vertuous Moderation; Can he believe theres the divine Ordinance, wheres ſuch humane inordinateneſſe; will he imagine that ſuch can be religious to Godward, who provide not things ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt before men? Dearly beloved Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians! let us learn Moderation, even for the Lords ſake, That ſo we may <hi>give none offence, neither to the Jew, nor to the Gentile, nor to the Church of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.32. (It is ſpoken of a modification in matters indifferent, and the diſcreet uſe of Chriſtian liberty therein.) And therefore it is admoniſhed (in things of a middle nature) to give ſcandal to none; leaſt the Church and Goſpel might hear ill: both from thoſe without and thoſe within. But that there might be ſuch a modeſt and moderate condeſcention on all parts in things lawful and expedient, as they without may not be deterred, but attracted, and they within not aggrieved, but confirmed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hereticks, It was immoderation
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170560:54"/> that made them ſuch; and nothing but Moderation can make them otherwiſe; will they eaſily be reconciled to that Church, wherein they obſerve leſſe har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and concord, then is to be found among themſelves? where there is ſuch branding one another for Antichriſtian and Babyloniſh, even about matters that are farre enough from entrenching upon the foundation. How have we provoked the old Popiſh challenge, to ſhew our Church, and to upbraid us of late, that we wanted ſo much as the face of a Church? Wot ye well (Brethren,) how many have turned Papiſts, upon ſcandal taken at our inteſtine broyles? Beſides, thoſe other that have confirmed themſelves in their errours. Alledging, that Church was built upon no foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that could keep it ſelfe into conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie. Come on therefore, in the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> all ye moderate ones, and let our moderation be known to them, I mean, not to tolerate or connive at them, but if not to convert, yet to convince them.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170560:55"/>3. Schiſmaticks, If our Moderation had been known to Schiſmaticks, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks immoderation had not been known to us. It is certain, there was too much of animoſity and acrimony of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit on either part. Either the bridle was not carried on handſomely, or the ſpurr was putting on too haſtily, or elſe theſe wilde and untamed beaſts, cunningly got the bit between their teeth, and ſo ranne headſtrong, with the reines upon their necks, to the caſting of their riders head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. And ſo they committed Religion with Policie, Doctrine with Diſcipline, Liberty with Licentiouſneſſe, Law with their own wills, Soveraign with Subjects, Nobles with Peaſants, Prieſts with Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, City with Countrey, to the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on almoſt of them all. But I hope they will now have the patience to hear a wor-of Moderation. Brethren! have ye done well &amp; aviſedly to rent Chriſts Coat? nay, have not ſome of you done as ill and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly as to pierce his ſide? was it hereſie that cauſed your ſchiſme? nay, what he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170560:55"/> hath your ſchiſme cauſed? was yours no more but a ſeparating from the Church? nay, was it not a turning the Church into a ſeparation? what ſay you elſe to your ſeparate Congregations? Moderation will tell you, that differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces about Diſcipline, can be no cauſes of Separation, (much leſſe of Subverſion) ſo the Doctrine be ſafe, and agreed on on either ſide; yea, and that the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es unity and peace ought not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed for every inferiour truth, or leſſer good, or ſeeming evil, much leſſe for every unſatisfied ſcruple, or taken ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal: leaſt of all, when all is but to ſatisfie mens malevolence, ambition, covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſingularity, peeviſhneſſe, blinde zeal, ignorance, and the like. If any man be irreſolv'd (God be bleſsed) we have (one and other) Lawes now again to appeal to; and not Armes: which (we may be ſure) will (with great Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) indulge the ſimply ſeduced; and ſeverely cenſure none, but ſuch of the Seducers, as wilfully will periſh in the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170560:56"/> gain-ſaying of <hi>Core.</hi> Come then, and let us meet in our Mothers boſom, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult moderately, and conſent. And (to ſtop the mouthes of our inſulting adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries) wee'll tell them of their incurable ſchiſmes, after (by Gods mercy) we have healed our own.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Weak Brethren, In my apprehenſion, Moderation hath a harder task to ſearch, and diſcerne ſuch as theſe, then ſhe hath to indulge or ſuccour them. For the Patient once found out, the wound is ſoon cured. Theſe for the moſt part are like ſome Beggars by the way ſide, that cover themſelves with ſcurfe and clouts, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending lameneſſe and diſeaſes, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to move compaſſion, for the readier obtaining of a larger Almes. But if they be thus ſickly minded indeed, the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes are, To diſcover their diſeaſe, and eſpecially the part affected, to bewail their infirmity to God-ward, and not to bemoan it only before men: to labour after their own cure, and not cheriſh their own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes themſelves; nay, and look that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170560:56"/> ſhould foſter them likewiſe. If they cannot yet be cured themſelves, yet (mean while) to be cautious of infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others. To repaire to the Hoſpital in that caſe provided, and not to delight in roving up and down. And there is Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration (the skilful Phyſician and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Chyrurgion) not to launce and feare, burn and cut, but to treat their ſores ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly; as readier to poure in oyle then vineger into their wounds: but if theſe apprehend not the Allegory, let me ſay to them in few and plain termes, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren! if your infirmity be neither prickt indeed, nor affected: Learn ye theſe Leſſons, as ye look for the favour of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, Do not think that ſhe muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes part with her ſtrength, if ye will alwayes keep your weakneſſe: nor that ſhe muſt therefore loſe her liberty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you will not attain to yours: or that ſhe muſt never follow the dictate of her own conſcience for the diſpenſing with yours. But let your conſcience be informed by her conſcience, and your
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170560:57"/> liberty ſubſcribing to her liberty; and your weakneſſe depending upon her ſtrength. So ſhall you neither take ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, nor ſhe give it, becauſe it is now mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately accorded betwixt you.</p>
               <p n="5">5. All, both Chriſtians and men, That by the means of known Moderation, men may become Chriſtians, and Chriſtians Saints, and Saints like the Angels of God in Heaven. That beholding our comely order, and godly converſation, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſound prophecying: if there come in one that believeth not, or one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, he may be convinc't of all, and judged of all; and thus the ſecrets of his heart may be made manifeſt; and ſo fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down on his face, he may worſhip God, and report that God is in us of a truth; That the heretical may know, that after the way which they call here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, ſo worſhip we the God of our fathers: yea, that their mouths may be ſtopt while they ſee our moderation, in yielding to all thats truth in them, even while we are oppoſing their errours. That the ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170560:57"/> and factious Zealots, may be convinc't that they are carnal, and walk as men, or are but Babes in Chriſt at the laſt. That the very Babes in Chriſt may ſee, we that are ſtrong are doing all to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to pleaſe our ſelves, but every one of us to pleaſe his neighbour to his edification. That every man may abide in the ſame calling wherein he is called, and therein abide with God. (Oh, I cannot but here call to mind the great immoderation of men ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing the bounds of their proper cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, the maine cauſe of all our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. While Coblers and Tinkers turn'd Preachers, Souldiers turn'd Lawgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Subjects turn'd Tyrants, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants turn'd Maſters) Moderation goes on in good leſſoning to make her ſelfe known. That ſuch as are called being Servants, ſhould be obedient to them that are their Maſters according to the fleſh, with fear and trembling, in ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their heart as unto <hi>Christ.</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170560:58"/> That Maſters forbear or moderate threatning, knowing that their Maſter alſo is in Heaven; neither is there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons with him. That chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould obey their parents in the Lord, for this is right. That parents ſhould not provoke their children to wrath, but bring them up in nurture and admonition of the Lord. That wives ſhould ſubmit themſelves unto their own husbands as unto the Lord. That husbands ſhould love their wives, even as Chriſt alſo loved the Church. That the aged men might be ſober, grave, temperate, &amp;c. the aged women in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour as becometh holineſſe, &amp;c. the young women that they be diſcreet, chaſte, keepers at home, &amp;c. the young men that they be ſober minded or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, That an Elder be not rebuked, but intreated as a father, and the younger men as brethren; The elder women as mothers, the younger as Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with all purity. All this is the end of Moderation, being made known to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170560:58"/> all men, yet even in all this ſhe boaſts not of things without her meaſure: but according to the meaſure of the rule or line, which God hath diſtributed to her; ſhe is a meaſure not only to reach to all men in general, but to every man in particular.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If Chriſtian Moderation muſt be known to all men; how much more then to one another; and to one as well as to another? Can we call that Moderation, which ſome men feign be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome; and yet flinch from it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others? Here they are much in the approof and applauſe of it: there they are altogether in the invective and calumny againſt it. Whatſoever theſe men are, certainly Moderation is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the ſame. Bidding us alwayes be moderate, firſt within our ſelves, then amongſt our ſelves; Bearing one anothers burdens, and ſo fulfilling the Law of Chriſt, pleaſing all men in all things, not ſeeking our own profit, but the profit of many, that they may be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170560:59"/> ſaved: Reſtoring a man that is overtaken in a fault, in the ſpirit of meekneſſe; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man conſidering himſelf, that he alſo may be tempted. Nevertheleſſe, ſo to withdraw our ſelves from every bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that walketh diſorderly, as noting that man, and having no company with him, that he may be aſhamed, yet not counting him as an enemy, but admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing him as a Brother. This is the way of Moderation, and would God it had been alwayes ſo with us! But oh Brethren! we cannot but be ſenſible of what meaſure you meted to us; what meaſure ſoever you expect from us. It was through your immoderations that we were made a ſpectacle unto the World, and to Angels, and to Men. We were fooles for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake, but ye were wiſe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we were weak, but ye were ſtrong: ye were honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but we were deſpiſed: ye were full and rich, and reigned as Kings without us, and would to God you had ſo reigned, as that we alſo might have
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170560:59"/> reigned with you. Ye were they that gave up your names to <hi>Christ,</hi> but you caſt out our names as evil. You cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led your ſelves the called, and the godly party: but we could heare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Antichriſtian, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy. Who ſowed the enmity (which hath ever ſince continued it) under the names of Epiſcopal and Presbyterian; well-affected and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants; Parliamentarians and Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts of Roundheads and Cavaliers? If you have a minde the enmity ſhould ceaſe, let theſe differential nicknames be objected or mentioned no more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us. Let Hereticks, and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, Anabaptiſts, Independents, Quakers and Levellers, and ſuch like, merit the perpetual inurement of ſuch diacritical appellations. But let us (in Gods Name) who are children and brethren, glory only to bear the Name of our Father. And in as much as we were baptized into one Name <hi>Chriſts:</hi> let us carry one Name before us, <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:170560:60"/> But if (by the immoderation ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on your part or ours) hearts be ſo tainted, and tongues ſo tipt, that theſe diviſive termes cannot be forgotten. Bleſſed be God for that Royal Advice, and that wiſe Counſel that ſits to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all our differences. By whoſe Authority (under God) we truſt (to make it a perfect Amneſtie or Act of Oblivion) all theſe ſhall (will we, nill we) be utterly put to ſilence. But we that are willing (I hope) ſhall herein alſo, and hereby, <hi>Let our Moderation be known to all men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2. <hi>The Motive.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord is at hand.</hi> Moderation cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly muſt be both a moſt excellent grace, and a moſt neceſſary duty. For more could not be ſaid to the inforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it. As will evidently appear, whether by this moving cauſe be meant the <hi>Lord Chriſts</hi> being near, or at hand.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In his Word and Goſpel which is nigh unto us, to inſtruct us ſufficiently, (yea, perfectly) to Moderation, in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170560:60"/> or minde, in perſons or places, and in all Affections, Actions, Paſſions, Speeches, Geſtures, Habits, Accidents, or Affairs. It is our line, cord, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, cannon, rule, both to regulate us in our faith, and moderate us in our manners alſo. As for things adiapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, or of a middle nature; hence likewiſe have we the true Touchſtone for their Trial, and the equal ballance to weigh them by. For if they be not here commanded, we know they are not good, or not good ſo to be made neceſſary, and ſo impoſed. And if they be not here forbidden, we know they are not evil, or not ſo evil, as to be thought unneceſſary, and ſo neglected. The word that moderates in all things elſe, hath left theſe things only to our Moderation. Nevertheleſſe, hath not in theſe things left Moderation (active or paſſive) to us as a thing indifferent, becauſe it is there commanded, yea, and the things ſo moderated, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently commanded alſo.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170560:61"/>2. By his Spirit: abiding with his Church to guide, or way lead it into all Truth: and into all order and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of it. For it ſeems good to the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> as well as to us, to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derating and directing, even in matters indifferent and ceremonial, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.28. And mark how moderating, <hi>to lay upon you no greater burden then theſe neceſſary things.</hi> If the Spirit and the Church think them neceſſary, it behoves us to think them no great burden; Nay (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to an emphatical kinde of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyrologie) <hi>the neceſſary things of theſe, or the things that are neceſſarily of theſe:</hi> For there may be ſome things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or neceſſarily to be adviſed, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, even in things of themſelves not neceſſary. Such as are in outward ceremonies, peace, order, unity, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, avoiding of ſcandal, preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſingularity and the like. And that this is according to the Moderation of the Spirit, no body (throughly ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that place) can deny.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170560:61"/>3. In his Preſential Providence, or Providential Preſence, <hi>viz.</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, approve, promote, and reward our Moderation. 1. To obſerve it And therefore let us behave our ſelves moderately, as children before the face of their Parents; and as Servants in the eye of their Maſters; <hi>It is the Lord, let us therefore gird our Coats unto us, (Joh.</hi> 21.7.) not only for natural, but Chriſtian modeſties ſake. Let us buy of him <hi>white raiment,</hi> (pure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Moderation) that we may be <hi>cloathed,</hi> (with order and comelineſſe) and that the <hi>ſhame of our nakedneſſe,</hi> (looſe and ſlovenly ſervices) do not appear, (not only for him, but for all the world to take notice of) <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18. But above all, let us be careful to cover the <hi>dung</hi> (of our filthy immoderations) <hi>for the Lord our God walketh in the midſt of us,</hi> Deut. 23.13, 14. 2. To ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it, of which we have proof ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and clear, both by his own will revealed, and in the eminent examples
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170560:62"/> of his Saints. 3. To promote and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it. For Moderation that meets with ſo many enormities, exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and obſtacles, to reſiſt or retard it: needs alwayes a more ſpecial pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and aſſiſtance of divine grace and power, both for the propagation and eſtabliſhment of it. 4. To reward it. For where had not Moderation (right Moderation) the bleſſing and comfort of peace and unity in the Church, of plenty and tranquillity to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, of plain ſatisfaction to conſciences, and of plenary contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all ſorts and conditions of men?</p>
               <p n="4">4. By his own inſtruments and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary means, ordain'd by him to that end. At hand now indeed, graciouſly &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully preſenting himſelf in preſenting to us, his great Vicegerent, our Royal Moderator (the very picture and pattern of moderation, modeſty, equity, clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, courteſie, gentleneſs, patience, and all that this preſent grace can be ſaid to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170560:62"/> or intend,) Ready (in his Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) to reſtore the Church to her former unity; the Kingdom to its anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent liberty, and both to their funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental and perpetual ſafety. All which (he well knows) is not to be done by any more apt expedient, and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent meanes, then in and by moderation, underſtood in her full and perfect ſenſe and ſway. At hand to help that <hi>multitude of Counſellours,</hi> for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of truth, of peace, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that neither good purpoſes may faile, nor the people fall. That matters may be conſulted and concluded, though not anſwerable to every mans immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate importunity: yet to the moderate expectation of all. At hand (we hope) in a godly, learned, grave Synod, where ignorance may be informed, weakneſs confirmed, perplexity reſolved, wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs convinced, and hereſie, faction and hypocriſie utterly exploded. And are all theſe at hand? and the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in all theſe? Hold then dear Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170560:63"/> Friends; and you my Brethren of the Miniſtry eſpecially; and let us not now run hand over head. Is it for us Privates, (I beſeech you) to preoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate and foreſtal the publick Authority? let it be a mark upon thoſe that have been too backward heretofore, to be now too forward: that ſo they may give ſome teſtimony of their pliable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to become ſtreight again, by overbending themſelves. But as for us, let us ſtay the time, and yet a little longer poſſeſs our ſouls in patience. If we have loſt, they will redeem it: if we have been diſgrac't, they will vindicate it; if we petition, they will anſwer it: only let us ſo moderate our ſelves, as to wait their moderation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Laſtly, by Death and the laſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; to viſit and do vengeance upon all the iniquities of Immoderation; when he ſhall ſtop, not only the mouths but the breaths of immoderate men, and cut them off from troubling his Church, yea, giving them over to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170560:63"/> immoderation of cutting off themſelves, and by being over-wicked and over-fooliſh, to die before their time. That is, by their own wickedneſs, rather then others Juſtice; yea, and that raging rather then repenting. And as for ſuch of them whom he hath ſuffered to die in their neſts: It was but a ſad ſigne that humane judgement was too mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate or mean, for their dreadful deſerts; and therefore he reſerved them (it is to be feared) to that of his own. As for all the reſt, Almighty God hath wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully made uſe of no more evident means then their own Immoderateneſs, (of pride, ambition, treachery, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, covetouſneſſe, luſts, oppreſſions,) whereby to ſupplant cunningly, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly overthrow one another. To the end, that Moderation (which is the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Church and State,) might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain (by his wiſe, juſt, and good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,) be reſtored and eſtabliſhed. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170560:64"/>
               <head>A Contemplative Invocation for <hi>MODERATION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Almighty, Everlaſting, and only wiſe Lord God! who judgeſt the world with righteouſneſſe, and thy people with equity. Are not thy wayes equal, O Righteous Lord! nay, are not our wayes unequal? unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wretches that we are. For we have gone aſtray like loſt ſheep, ſtumbling from the ancient path, the good old way; loving to wander in wayes not caſt up. Our whole life and way hath been either a backſliding, or a halting, or a turning either to the right hand or to the left. We have not walked with a right foot, no not in our beſt actions; but have ſtarted aſide like broken bows, even in our beſt aimes. Our manifold tranſgreſſions in all their inordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170560:64"/> and immoderations (the fire in our boſomes, and rottenneſs in our bones,) are not unknown to thee; who markeſt all our ſteps, and telleſt all our fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttings. Now, becauſe it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee to moderate thine own Law, by the Goſpel of thine own Sonne. Moſt humbly and heartily we beſeech thee, (for the meekneſſe and Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> our bleſſed Saviour) to pardon and heal our backſlidings, and grant, that by the leading of thy gracious ſpirit, our wayes may be ſo directed, that our ſteps may be order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to thy Word. That our eyes may look right on, and our eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids look ſtraight before us, to ponder the paths of our feet, that all our wayes may be ordered aright, and we turne neither to the right hand nor to the left, but wholly removing our feet from evil. And for as much as it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee in great mercy, and after a wonderful manner to free our necks
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170560:65"/> from that iron yoke of thoſe mighty Hunters and Hammers of the Earth, our Egyptian Task-maſters, that ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged us with ſcorpions: and haſt in like manner reſtored to our Head our Nurſing Father, to carry us in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, to draw us with cords of a man, and bands of love; Thou that haſt thus raiſed him up in righteouſneſſe, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh thou the Throne of his Kingdom as the dayes of Heaven; direct thou his wayes, and prolong his dayes, that thy pleaſure may proſper in his hands. And teach us now to be ſubject unto the higher powers, and to ſubmit our ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, giving to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that be <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and to God the things that be Gods. He whoſe is Counſel and ſound Wiſdom, ſo coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel our multitude of Counſellours, that they may be to us in ſtead of eyes, that their good and wiſe purpoſes may not be diſappointed, nor the people fall;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170560:65"/> but that the peace and ſafety of us all may be therein; Vouchſafe ſo to order and moderate all thoſe, to whom thou haſt committed the Word and Miniſtry of Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, that they may pray and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech men, in <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſtead, to be reconciled firſt to God, and then to one another: Approving their Miniſtry, by being indeed the Salt of the Earth, (through their diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and moderation) ſalted with fire (of love as well as zeal) And never ſuffer that Salt ſo to be infatuated, or loſe the ſavour, that it be thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth good for nothing, but to be caſt out, and trodden under foot of men. Let it be our ſtudy and care, (not others reproaching) firſt (Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician-like) to heal our ſelves: that having caſt out the beame out of our own eye; we may ſee the more clearly to pull the mote out of our brothers eye. Purge us therefore
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170560:66"/> (we pray thee) from all immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſſe of paſſions, affections, or affectations: thoſe dead flies, that cauſe the ointment, (which ſhould heal our diviſions) to ſend forth a ſtinking ſavour: A very little of which leaven is enough to leaven, or ſoure the whole lump, or maſſe of all our actions and affaires. Farre be it from us, to be ſo unwiſe as to meaſure our ſelves by our ſelves, or to compare our ſelves among our ſelves; be it our part rather not to pleaſe our ſelves, but every one to pleaſe his neighbour for his good to edification. Lead us (O Lord) in thy Righteouſneſſe becauſe of our enemies: make therefore thy way ſtreight before our faces; leaſt they blaſpheme and ſay, Where is now their God? where is now their Church? Do thou quaſh thoſe Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atrice-Egges in the ſhell, which he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks have hatched, that they break
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170560:66"/> not forth into vipers; and ſo thy children be not only ſtarved with ſtones in ſtead of bread, but even poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with Serpents in ſtead of Fiſhes. And for as much as a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome divided againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand; knit thou thy Word, the Church, and our own conſciences ſo together, that the gates of hell may not prevail to break this threefold cord. Break down therefore the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition-wall, and let the enmity be ſlaine: that we of one body, one ſpirit, one faith, may be of one minde in the Lord. And not divide the child, nor halt between two, nor ſerve two Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, nor couch between two burdens. Nevertheleſſe, let us not be ſo preciſe, as to forbid even the caſting out of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in thy Name, becauſe they follow not with us. Nor yet ſo cenſorious as to ſay, he that is not with us is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us; but to ſay more aptly to this purpoſe, he that is not againſt us, is
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170560:67"/> with us. Sith there may be the ſame ſubſtance of truth, though not exactly under the ſame circumſtances, yet (we beſeech thee) ſtirre us up to the keeping of the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. And ſeeing ſo many as are perfect are thus minded: if any man be otherwiſe minded, do thou (Lord God) remark it to him in good time. Howbeit, whereunto we have already attained, grant us to walk after the ſame rule, minding the ſame thing. Neither ſuffer us to judge one another any more, but to judge this rather, that no man put a ſtumbling block, or an occaſion to fall in his brothers way: To the intent our good of liberty be not ill ſpoken of either by one or other. That ſo we ſin not againſt the brethren, wounding their weak conſcience, or ſet them at nought by our not walking according to charity. Abate therefore the vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous zeale or emulation of all ſuch
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170560:67"/> Sonnes of Thunder, that are for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but ſire from Heaven, not knowing what ſpirit they are of, in contending ſo bitterly to break the bruiſed reed, and quench the ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flax, wholly bent to binde heavy burdens upon mens ſhoulders, yet can even therein ſo diſpenſe with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as ſcarce to touch them with one of their fingers. Be pleaſed withal to rectifie and eſtabliſh their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are yet children in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, toſſed to and fro (like waves of the ſea) and carried up and down with every wind of doctrine, by the ſleights and cogging juglings of men. Who are ſo ſuperſtitious in their ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſities, as not to ſow in obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the winde, neither yet to reap in their regarding of the clouds, and thoſe no other but clouds without raine. As they abound in their own ſenſe, ſo let them be fully perſwaded in their own mindes, that to the clean
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170560:68"/> all things are clean: neither let them preſume to call that common or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, which thou thy ſelf haſt clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Diſcover to them their owne nakedneſſe, that ſeek no further, but to ſow to themſelves Fig-leaves of frivolous pretences, and their lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe too, that truſts only to the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken reeds of their own wilfulneſſe: and ſo kick againſt the pricks of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority; and ſtrive againſt the ſtream of univerſal conſent. Quiet each one of thoſe querulous ſpirits, and malecontents amongſt us, who (worſe then the wilde Aſſe) brayeth, when he hath graſſe; or the Ox that loweth over his fodder. Confute them likewiſe to their faces, that dote about queſtions, and ſtrife of words, with perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt mindes, and deſtitute of the truth. Pull down and deface thoſe whited walls, and painted ſepulchres, where there is no other cleanſing but
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170560:68"/> that of the out-ſide of the platter. That compaſſe ſea and land to make a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelite, that ſtrain at gnats and ſwallow camels, and put on ſheeps clothing to no other purpoſe, but to the rending of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſeamleſſe coat. Quench the tailes of thoſe ſmoaking firebrands, whoſe peeviſhneſſe and perverſeneſſe hath proved ſmoak to our eyes, vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to our teeth, and thornes in our ſides. Teach us with ſubmiſſion to admire thy wiſe diſpenſation, of clean and unclean beaſts in the Ark. And therefore ſo moderate us, as that we may neither be too haſty, nor ſevere, in offering our ſelves, to the plucking up the tares from amidſt the wheat; leaſt we root up the wheat alſo with them. But let us be content to poſſeſs our ſoules in patience, if both muſt grow together till the harveſt, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, help us that are of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to have no communion with thoſe that are known to be of <hi>Belial.</hi> For what
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170560:69"/> hath the wheat to do with the chaffe? Remove from us all ſuch as would remove the ancient Landmarks, and break the common hedge, and let their own conſcience be the firſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent that bites them. Confound both the tongues and the hands of all thoſe tumultuous ones, <hi>children of noiſe and clamour,</hi> that are given to change: who to build their <hi>Babel,</hi> would not care to turne the whole earth upſide down. Free us evermore from the tyranny and ſlavery of men overwiſe and overjuſt, that wring the noſe till they bring forth blood, ſtrip the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of their clothing, ſell the poor for a paire of ſhoes, that turne judgment to wormwood, cauſe truth to fall in the ſtreets, and equity cannot enter. That have ſet ſervants to rule not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly over us, but over Princes: And (like <hi>Iſmaels</hi> own ſonnes) not caring whoſe hand could be againſt them; ſo their hand might be but ſtrong enough
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170560:69"/> againſt every man. Uncover their skirts, open their own faces, and let them be cloathed with no more but the ſhame and diſhonour of fanatick God-mockers, that have faſted for ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſſe, bowing down the head like a Bulruſh, and yet put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the finger nevertheleſſe. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their brethren, and caſting them out for thy names ſake, and yet ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, let God be glorified, yea, killing them, and thinking they have done thee good ſervice. Put to confuſion that harlots forehead that cannot bluſh; break to pieces that crooked thing which will not be made ſtreight; and who ſo will daſh againſt that rock, let it fall upon him again and grinde him to powder. Ariſe, (O Lord!) and diſappoint the cunning craftineſſe of men that lie in wait to deceive. And let not the children of this world boaſt themſelves in their
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170560:70"/> generation, far wiſer then the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light. But graciouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent us with thy watchfull Eye, that while <hi>Judas</hi> is awake, the Diſciples may not be found aſleep. Laugh to ſcorne the vanity, and negligence of all them, that in the work of the Lord, build up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sands; labour for, ſow, and feed on the wind; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but beate the ayre: and ſo ranne altogether in vayne. Stirre up the ſlothfull ſpirits of ſuch as (ſluggard like) only fold their hands, and cry out (at every dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty) there is a Lyon in the way. But they that pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and beare good will to <hi>Zion;</hi> comfort all their hearts, and cover all their heads, and ſtrengthen all their hands; to be valiant for the truth, fight the good fight to the finiſhing of their courſes, and receiving of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170560:70"/> the Crown. Satisfie, or rather ſtint thou the ſtomacks of thoſe Daughters of the Horſe-leach, that cry continually give, give; and never ſay it is enough. And let it alwayes be a ſnare to thoſe ſacrilegious God-robbers, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure that which is holy, and yet never once vow to make inquiry. Sopp thoſe ſtolne waters, and break the ſtaffe of <hi>that bread of ſecrecies</hi> which are ſweet and pleaſant to the thief, that entred not in by the door: to the end that he who planted the Vineyard, may eate of the Fruit; and he that feedeth the Flock, may taſte of the milke: and the Ox treading out the Corne, may not be muzled; but that the labourer may be accounted worthy of his hire. So order thou every man in the calling wherein he is called, that he may therein abide with God, not walking diſorderly,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170560:71"/> like a buſibody; nor wandring from his place, like a Bird from the neſt, nor exerciſeing himſelf in great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or in things that are to high for him; neither yet eſſaying or ſeeking great things for himſelf. Eſpecially not medling with the ſtrife that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to him; leaſt it ſo falls out that he holds a dogg by the eares. So moderate all our ſenſual appetites, that we may remember to put the knife to our throats. And though we have found hony, yet temper us ſo as only to eate ſo much as is ſufficient for us; leaſt we be filled therewith, and vomit it up again. Give us neither poverty, nor riches; but feed us with food convenient for us. And having food and rayment, grant us therewith to be content. As knowing both how to be abaſed, and how to abound. That in all caſes and conditions our mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (both of body and minds) may be approved by thee; and known to all
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170560:71"/> men. Grant this for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (our only Mediatour, and Moderators) ſake. To which bleſſed Son of thine, with thee (mercifull <hi>Father</hi>) and the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> be the worſhip and the glory, now, and ever, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170560:72"/>
            <head>A CATALOGUE of ſome Books print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the Gun in <hi>Ivy-lane.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>The <hi>Alliance of Divine Offices,</hi> exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting all the Liturgies of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: by <hi>Hamon l' Eſtrange</hi> Eſq</item>
               <item>The Souls Conflict being 8. Sermons, preacht at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended, by the late <hi>Dr. Hewyt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Browns</hi> Sepulchral Urns, and <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> of <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Two <hi>Eſſayes</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Marriage.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Queens</hi> Exchange, by Mr. <hi>R. Brome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Five new Playes by Mr. <hi>R. Brome,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before printed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> out of <hi>Eden,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Speed,</hi> an excellent piece of Husbandry.</item>
               <item>Poemes on ſeveral perſons and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, by No body muſt know whom.</item>
               <item>Crums of Comfort 43 times printed.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170560:72"/>
               <item>Moſt of Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> Books.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Shepherds</hi> Duty of Conſtables in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>St. <hi>Bonaventures</hi> Soliloquies in 24.</item>
               <item>Healths Improvement in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. uſing the Nature and Method uſed in this Nation.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Treatiſe of Converſion in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>That long-expected piece, The <hi>Survey of the Law;</hi> containing directions how to proſecute, or defend Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons brought at Common Law by <hi>William Gliſſon</hi> Eſq</item>
               <item>A Second Ternary of Sermons, by the Learned Dr. <hi>Stewart</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>The Elements of Water-drawing, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> the price 6 d.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Sprats</hi> plague of <hi>Athens</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>Jews in <hi>America,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Thorowgood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Royal Buckler</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, or a Lecture for Traitors.</item>
               <item>A ſhort view of ſome late remarkable Tranſactons, leading to the happy Government, under our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soveraign King <hi>Charles</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:170560:73"/> Second, by <hi>L' eſtrange</hi> Eſq,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Rump,</hi> or all the Songs and Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lads made upon thoſe who would be a Parliament, and were but the Rump of an Houſe of Commons, five times diſſolved.</item>
               <item>The Pourtraicture of his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie King <hi>Charls</hi> the Second, from his Birth 1630. till this preſent year 1660. being the whole Story of his eſcape at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> his Travels and Troubles.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:170560:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
